and not to fall, and he will be the light of the nations and the hope of those whose hearts are
troubled. All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him, and they will praise and bless
and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits, 1st denoc, chapter 48, verses 4 through 5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels, demons,
and saints. In our time, many year into break free of the prison of a flat, secular...
materialism to see and to know reality as it truly is.
What is this spiritual reality like?
How do we engage with it well?
How do we permeate every day life with spiritual presence?
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick
and Father Stephen De Young
host this live Colin show,
focused on enchantment in creation.
The union of the scene and unseen as made by God
and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord.
spirits. Hey good evening all you giant killers, you dragon slayers, all of you who are recovering from
Christmas. So unless you're on the old calendar, you got not quite two weeks left to go. So hang in
there you guys. Christ is born Merry Christmas glorify him. I think you're listening to it extra
time for the bygifts because they forgot. I mean, that's a good, I mean, it's a good reason,
right? On the show? Or as a Dutchman.
Yeah, if it's because they could get everything on sale on the 26. Hey,
that's what you guys do. All your all your props for that St. Nicholas day. Is that when the
Dutch do the weeks? Yeah, we do it back on center class. Yeah, December 6. Yeah. Yeah.
Well, it is the Lord of spirits podcast. And my co-host whom you just heard Father Stephen
De Young is coming to you live from Lafayette, Louisiana. I'm Father Andrew Stephen
in a meis Pennsylvania, the forests of Penn.
So if you are listening to us.
You can call us at 855-237-2346 and you can see a second half of the show, and our very
own Matyska Trudy will be taking those calls.
Tonight we're going to be talking about patron saints, but first a word from our sponsors.
The Lord of Spirits podcast is brought to you by our listeners.
Hey, that's all of you.
And the Antioch in Men.
The Antioch in Men abbreviated Amen, a men's ministry of the diocese of Miami in the southeast
within the anti-ocun-
Orthodox Christian Archdiocese of North America will be hosting the first ever Antiochian
men conference and retreat from March 7th to 9th, 2024 at the Woodland Christian Camp
and Retreat Center in Temple, Georgia, with the theme, the Audacity of Manhood, Strength
through virtuous work.
The event will feature guest speakers, outdoor activities, sports workshops, campfire fellowship,
and more.
include his great-sp worship necklace, our very own father.
Stephen D. Young, Father Hans J.
That's you, man.
You're going to be there?
Think about it.
I guess, yeah.
And also, Father Jacob Undoone,
this event will incorporate the best
aspects of camping conferences and retreats
into a first of its kind experience
for Orthodox Christian men.
Men ages 18 and older, welcome to register.
Early bird registration is $149 per person.
And that includes lodging for two nights and six meals.
And that's about as cheap as it gets.
I just think about that.
To learn more in register.
There's two Dutch priests involved.
Yeah, there you go.
So to learn more in register, go to antiokinmen.org.
Click on the banner at the top.
Again, that's antiokinmen.org.
This may or may not become germane at the retreat,
but when I was thinking about the outdoor activities and stuff,
you know what there is not enough of any more in this world?
so many things, but tell me, Father Stephen.
Whittling.
So will this be like a competition of whittling?
I don't know.
This is I'm just thinking about this.
It seems to me like whittling is a good productive pastime
that has has fallen into obscurity in our modern world.
Well, you don't have to use a wood around, right?
You made a pocket knives anymore.
You made our conference have a D&D tournament.
So maybe you can have forced whittling with the answer.
I don't think we'd have-
to force it. I think just a couple of bunch of knives and pieces of wood and magic
again. Well, it's wooded. You don't go grab some wood. You know, you can just find wood.
If you have a handy pocket knife, there you go. You might have some trouble getting it on the plane
to get out there, but you know, there will be some available for probably not. Probably not,
but we can figure something out. It's not that far from Atlanta. Yeah. Yeah. You can go get a pocket knife.
a big run on whittling knives.
This is not to be this, you know, Swiss Army varieties.
something. You know, straight ahead. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Again, when
we get kids with the fingernail and toenail clippers and the
pocket. What would the Swiss army have done without those
things? I think it's the key to their victory in every major
war they've stayed neutral in. So tonight though, our topic is
patron states. We've been asked about this a lot actually. And
Especially our Protestant friends might find the Orthodox practice.
of having patron saints for people, places, churches, groups, etc.
Kind of weird and frankly unbiblical.
Is it though?
Is there a biblical basis for this element of Christian life?
What about those who say that this is just a whitewashing of pagan polytheism
to love alliteration?
Calling upon various gods for different purposes.
What do we do with the similarities between how pagans treat their gods
God's and how Christians relate to patrons saying
so father Steven, our patron saints really just thinly veiled paganism.
No.
Thickly veiled maybe or no, not at all. No, veiling not even unveiled paganism.
Yeah, there's no paganism. Yeah. You move the curtain. There's no paganism there.
Yeah, yeah, tonight we're gonna be going back to some of what we're gonna be talking about.
about is going to be sort of bringing together some things we talked about in the earliest episodes of the show.
Yeah.
Between Mexican radio broadcasts and power outages.
Oh, man.
Back in the day.
And we're also going to be trying to sort of synthesize that in a coherent way that hopefully we'll answer some of the questions that we get consistently all the time.
Related to this.
Yeah.
And I don't want to spend too long on this, not that, you know, you know how I hate digressing.
But even the way like it means, right, we have to think sometimes about how things are framed.
Right. Like things needing to have a biblical basis. Right. What does that mean?
I'm sorry.
It means I found it in the Bible somewhere and on that basis, I'm going to do it on I'm going to argue that this is referring to that and of course anyone who
Disagrees with that is going to say no, it doesn't refer to that right right right right right
But the book is just a word meaning I do not agree with your doctrine. Yes
This but this assumes a couple things about a text that aren't possible
Number one that a text is not based on anything
Hmm.
You can have a text as ultimate.
You can't have a text as ultimate.
Yeah.
Because first of all, the rules of grammar.
The language itself has to be a...
Well, the language itself has to underlie the text.
Right.
Yeah.
Number one.
And number two, for example,
this is a text reporting historical events
than those historical events underlie the text.
Right? Yep. The events didn't spring from the text. The text came from the events
and give a perspective and interpretation of the events.
Why am I bringing this up at all right now? This is not just me taking a shot at our Protestant
friends about the coherency or lack thereof of Solascriptura, but to say we have to approach
this kind of thing when we're looking at
a historic practice of the church, which we know without a doubt is a practice that went
back to at least the end of the first beginning of the second century.
Minimally.
Right.
Minimally, to assume that those kind of historic practices were quote unquote based on
like the New Testament text is not a it's not a coherent way of thinking about it.
Right.
especially because those texts don't even claim to be
that kind of book like they're not a manual like a briskot manual.
Here's how you, although even Boy Scout manual, right?
You still have to be part of a group that shows you how to be a Boy Scout.
Right. And it doesn't cover every single topic.
No, that might come up in the life of a Boy Scout.
Right. It makes no claim to be that comprehensive.
Right. But yeah.
the scriptures aren't even a manual, right, in that sense. So we would expect to find places where
practices that existed at the time are reflected in the text, right? But based on the type of text
that the scriptures are, we wouldn't expect to find, well, okay, here's how sainthood works.
Here's what makes someone a saint. Here's how patron saints work. Here's that, right, we wouldn't
expect to find that in the Bible.
Yeah, it would be weird to find that the Bible.
Yeah, there's almost nothing that is like, and here's how this works.
And here's what all of this means.
Like the closest you get is Leviticus telling you how to do sacrifices and that kind of thing.
Right.
Because that is sort of functioning as a manual.
The book of Leviticus is kind of a manual.
Look it up.
Here's the details of how you do this.
Although it's how to be a leabuff.
Yeah, there's still gaps.
Yeah, still a lot of gaps.
But the scripture is all on there.
So yeah.
And so there are all kinds of things, right? And this lies behind all kinds of bad arguments, right? Like
Why does the word Trinity appear in the Bible?
Right and all these other kinds of arguments like well, there are places where we can see in the Bible it reflects
A belief in the Trinity or minimally something very much like it, right?
right? But yeah, it's not laid out anywhere.
because nothing is. That's not how the Bible works. Right. Like, so this isn't either.
Right. This isn't either. So what we have to do is we have to look at how the Bible
talks about, uses the word that gets translated as saint. Right. How that word is used,
how the people
whom that is applied or discussed, how they're related to and various other things to determine,
oh, okay, so this is the structure of what was believed and taught and experienced by the first
hearers of this text. This is how they understood reality to function. This is how they encountered
God, how they experience God, how they worship.
God, right, flexed in the text by the way the text speaks, the way the text speaks. But
it's not going to be like laid out in the text. Yeah. And about to move on from this and
say, wait, topic per se. But the fact again, that something is not laid out in the text
but also, therefore, does not mean it didn't exist.
Right. Obviously a lot of things exist in the ancient world that are not specifically put in the text. And we should probably also say that a lot of important things existed that are not laid out in the text. Right. Right. So there was some concrete detailed structure to temple worship and tabernacle worship and synagogue worship. Right. Beyond what is laid out formally in scripture.
Right. And the fact that that is never laid out in and early Christian worship in the New Testament,
the fact that that's never laid out in detail doesn't mean it didn't exist that there was no pattern.
And it doesn't mean that the pattern is an important.
Right. Because again, it's not setting out a guide. It's not setting out a manual.
And so the fact that the particular way in which humans relate to departed saints in its every
detail is not laid out anywhere in the scriptures.
Or he's not in any one place, especially doesn't mean there was no such relationship.
Right. People just stopped thinking about their dead Christian loved ones. Right.
Or right, they did something at funerals.
Right.
Right. Check the body in a ditch.
Right. They had them prayers were set. Right. Right.
There was an understanding.
And so we're looking through the scriptures, through other means, to determine what the
shape of that was.
Right?
Not looking, say, oh, well, we don't see that laid out in the scripture.
So it doesn't matter or there wasn't one or, right?
We just assume, right, that it's, since it's not stated, it's not important or doesn't
exist.
Right?
Assume the Roman cat.
Catholics are wrong. I mean, we could safely assume that, right?
You had to take a shot at our Catholic friends as well, right?
Well, that was seat now. There's there's levels of sarcasm surrounding that comment.
So I know. I know. I know. I know. I'm just saying.
I've just said we, one of our comments we got on Facebook was someone wrote
that she is one of our Protestant friends waiting for more shots.
Oh, right next to another we
actually have a listener from Malaysia, listening right now from Malaysia, where it's like 816 in the morning.
So we're the morning show in Malaysia.
Wow.
I've got that.
I feel like I should have a coffee mug and smile more.
Talk about the weather.
So so as as I said in the midst of that rant, which may or may not be the last rant of the evening,
We have to kind of start with
Okay, when we talk about a saint, right, what are we even talking about?
Right because that gets used in a lot of different ways.
Right, I mean people will just say somebody's a saint because they were like a really good or really nice person.
Yeah, right, it's sort of like calling them a mench, right? Like there's this.
Or sometimes it's a way of
of saying that their spouse must be a real nightmare.
Yeah.
Yes. Yes. Oh, and we do have we say it is guaranteed by being married to me. Yes.
Yes. My wife's state is also guaranteed.
We have a listener from Lithuania where it is two, 17 in the morning. So
don't be a one-upper Lithuanian dedication man.
This is someone I know actually. So okay. Yes. All the love.
right, so this just gets used.
these different ways, right? Or, you know, El Santo, possibly the greatest luchador of all time,
right? At least the one who made the best movies. I was not expecting that.
Go look up some El Santo, but they're amazing. Anyway. Really? Oh yeah, yeah. They're the Elvis
movies of Mexico like nice seriously so
Yeah, and he's of course the same or you know if we want to really dig in the crates right Roger Moore
Later on Val Kilmer the same right
It gets used gets used in those ways
Some people just tack it in front of any old person from the Bible
Yeah, yeah
Or any old person from the early church
like just a title like miss
or sir, right? But the root and the root isn't that well hidden in English if you know any Latin
at all, right? Is of course a holy one, right? And if we're talking about Greek, we're talking about
IEOS, right? If you get icons with Greek inscriptions, you will see this. Sometimes in a calligraphy
where it's a little tricky to make it out unless your Greek is pretty solid. But...
You will see that in front of the names of people and icons.
That is translating Kutashim in Hebrew, various similar words in Aramaic and you can see
cognates if you know any Arabic, you know, Kudus is holy.
This is holiness.
Right. I was about to say sanctity, but sanctity is also just the one from some of this in Latin,
which reads holy, right? So this is a holy one, right? And holy here is a noun, or is an adjective.
Holy here is an adjective, right? Even when it's being used substantively, meaning you could take
and adjective and you could use it some-
positively, right, to say a holy one, a good one, an evil one, right?
But it's still an adjective. You just have an implied subject, right? Right. So holy is not by
itself a noun. Right. And the importance of this is that when we're talking about whether
This is applied to a human or as we're about to talk about an angelic being, or God is
described as holy.
It is an adjective.
It doesn't mean that, okay, this is a holy man.
So he is like a different species.
He is a different thing than just a man.
Yeah.
He's a man.
Right.
Yeah.
Subscripter
of that man, or a descriptor of that angelic being, or a descriptor of God. Right? It's an adjective.
Another example of this much debated in Orthodox circles and nowhere else is at the end of the Lord's
prayer, right? Where the adjective evil occurs. Or the evil one. That is it evil or the evil one,
and write.
Is it being used substantively?
Is essentially the question, right?
That of course being the opposite, okay?
So originally where we see this word occur
as a substantive noun, right?
Holy one or holy ones.
In the Hebrew Bible, in the Old Testament,
it's referring to angelic beings.
Right. To the holy ones who surround the divine throne. Right. Glorious is God amongst his
holy ones. Right. And because of that, so in English, right, this gets translated in various
ways. Right so a lot of times what we're used to is in the old testament.
it'll get translated as holy ones, in the New Testament it'll get translated as saints.
Which makes no sense because it's really, even though it's Hebrew and the Old Testament
Greek and the New, it's really the same idea. Right. Right. So a lot of orthodox,
liturgical translations and things have responded to this by always translating it saints.
Sure, yeah. Which then confuses people.
Yeah, which yeah, which is why you then get the question
Wait, can we call angels saint like saint Michael?
Saint because they think of saint as being something that is about holy humans
But we'll get you know, I don't want to steal much of our own thunder here
Right, but we also we also think about God being you know wondrous in his saints
Yeah, it's like wait what? Yeah
Right, if you read the original and you know it's
wonders among his holy ones. Right. So even amongst the array, the arrayed angelic beings,
God is wondrous, right, meaning far more wondrous than they. Right. Is the idea there, right?
In English, because we use saints, does it work out there? And brief mini rant, my pet peeve,
is the entrance prayers with
were in the liturgy and
investors, which were at one point
translated as saying that God
resteth in his saints. Yeah, or
it also seen in the Holy Place
or well, so people got confused by
rests in the saints like what does
that mean? Right? Yeah. Yeah. And so
they looked at it and decided even
though it's the plural, the
translated as rest in the holy place.
Now, I don't know which holy place they're referring to.
There's a whole series of questions there about that translation.
Not just that they're translating the plateaus as they go.
But if you look at the prayers surrounding it,
the prayers surrounding it talk about God and or Christ, right?
meaning the father and or Christ being enthroned upon the chairman.
So it's literally got to resteth like Sidith on his holy ones.
That's what it says.
And can mean on in Greek for those who don't know anything with Greek.
Yeah, it could be on or in.
That's what it means.
So that's why many read it, right?
Everybody translates that weirdly.
I don't know why, right?
But so the idea here is that originally we're talking angels and it's translated holy ones.
You could do the opposite thing and translate it as holy or holy ones all the time.
Right. So we say Saint Paul, we're talking about holy Paul.
The holy Paul. Yeah. Which is literally, yeah. That would be a word for word translation of the Greek,
by your spavlers.
Yes, holy Paul Paul the holy Paul the holy one right
Peter the holy one right
Um
I'm reminded of in in idiocracy
St. God Memorial Hospital, but that's a whole other time
Yeah.
Um, so, um, but, but so this is where we're originally it's angelic being.
It comes to be spoilers for our second half applied to humans.
Right, right.
But so our side is a turn.
Now, we have to parallel this, right, with another very common term that's used for those same beings.
in the Hebrew Bible and in the Old Testament.
And that is the term, God's.
Yeah, which and he'd be right with a lowercase G. Yeah lowercase G everybody lowercase G. Yeah Hebrew Elohim in Greek Tha'i
Both are used in Old Testament and then you know the New Testament Greek Tha'i
Yeah, and
so
That is often very deliberately obscured in translations
Because it gives people the heebie Gb's
Um.
Because as we've talked about the show before in the 16th and 17th centuries, we came up with this idea of monotheism and then decided that has to be what the Bible teaches.
Meaning there's only one God that exists.
Right. And so you get these odd translations to try to cover up where it says that.
That of course, then once you get into the 18th and 19th centuries.
got people get caused the opposite reaction of, oh, here's what they're trying to hide
that it's actually the Bible is actually polytheist.
Man, we really are partying like it's 2020 here on the podcast.
This is literally stuff from our very first episode.
Yes, yes.
So we're going somewhere with it though.
Yeah, yeah.
It's somewhere retrid.
And hopefully, I'll maintain electricity.
So this will be a little smoother presentation.
How many hurricanes come?
Louisiana and in December.
None but hey, whether is doing interesting things right now, it is.
Imagine how crazy it would be if global warming was real.
Anyway, that just that comment just got everyone mad called climate change.
That everyone was outraged at that comment.
Send your letters to father Andrew at a debate.
So yes.
So this was taken as evidence, right?
Well, well into the 20th century,
this was, you know, they want you to think
that the Bible's one of the estic, but really it's polytheism.
And that, of course, especially if we're talking
about the 19th century, we have this overriding,
presupposition of an evolutionary hypothesis
that religion like everything else starts really simple
and then gets more and more complex over time.
Um, I won't go off on another digression, but which is really dumb, right?
It's sort of as the idea that, uh, you know, one day there's, there's a primitive human,
right, with a stick who comes up with the idea.
I guess that he should ask the stick for favors.
I don't know how exactly this would work in concrete terms.
Yeah.
How do you invent the idea of a god?
I don't know of religion where there is none.
I don't even know how this works, but in theory.
But basically, and that somehow monotheism is way more complex than polytheism.
Yeah.
And then if you go with the originators and perfectors of this kind of theory, that somehow 19th
century German Lutheranism is way more complex than like
paganism. I don't follow that either. But the argument is that that's the case. And so that
what you see, particularly they would say in the Old Testament, is a move from a primitive
Israelite polytheism that eventually evolves into the
modern concept of monotheism. Right. And so, yeah, there must be remnants leftover, right,
of their previous polytheistic stuff. So anything you could find that could be interpreted
as polytheistic, like gods in the plural or anything even alluding to that, this is the
early stuff. Yeah. And then anything that sounds like modern monotheism, this is very late
And the fun thing about...
this is, that in order for this to be to sort of be
consonant with the biblical texts that we have, you have to
decide that in what is literally the most combed over book in
human history, that they somehow accidentally left in all of
these references to their former polytheism, just their
editing is really bad.
really bad. Like how many tens or hundreds of thousands or millions of people read it before
it, you know, like, or heard it read and said, wait a minute, that's that polytheism,
you know, edit that off there. No one noticed, you know, but I mean, but that's how you have
that's how you have to, how you have to shake it out if you're going to try to make that
argument based on how to text. We talk about their theology stuff, be back, but before, but
to be fair to them.
They they try to argue that there was some kind of text taboo like this is the sacred text you can't change it
Well, but part in parcel of their whole argument is that it was edited over time
So the person doing the last editing job could not also have had a text changed taboo at the same time because he's changing the text
Yeah, right? Like you you can't do both at the same time, but it's a
nicely self fulfilling argument, right?
Because anything anybody points to, right?
You point to a tax that sounds kind of polytheistic and they say,
well, that's just, that's early.
Yeah.
And you point to what that sounds more monotheistic.
They say, well, that's late.
And it's like, well, how do you know that it evolved this way?
And that'll say, well, because the early texts are polytheistic and the later texts are monotheistic.
And you say, well, how do you know that this is an early text?
Because it's polytheistic.
Right.
So it's a tight circularity.
Right? Right.
You're still just making this completely circular argument.
Right?
And the self fulfilling prophecy. Right?
And worse than that, worse than just being a bad argument. Right?
I mean, you could make a bad argument that ends up being correct.
Like, I could argue for the truth badly.
Right. So just the fact that this is a horrible argument at a shoddy way of working with the
text doesn't necessarily mean the conclusion is wrong. Right. What proves the conclusion
wrong is all the actual evidence we have. Yes.
Yeah. Which if this were a true model, you would expect that as you go, that later texts
would have fixed that we know
or later, not that we're just saying,
but saying.
We know once we actually know that it would have fewer and fewer references to God's plural, right, right?
Divine plurality in any sense, fewer and fewer as you go, right?
Yeah, so if we find tax say I don't know in the Dead Sea scrolls
That we know for a fact we're written in the second or third century BC after
At least the lion share of the Hebrew Bible was done. They should reflect that later monotheistic consensus, right?
Yeah.
Bye.
But if you do the math, which we have them fancy computers who can do this now, you find
that the text, the non-biblical texts in the Dead Sea Scrolls actually have more references
to gods in the plural than the biblical texts.
Yes, second temple Jewish texts use God's plural approvingly way more
than the canonical Hebrew Bible.
Right.
So, and it's not just true of the Densy schools.
The Densy schools are an example, right?
You look at phyllo, phyllo uses gods in the plural
and it doesn't ever problem with it.
Josephus, the same thing.
What we find is that the exact opposite is the case,
that by the time you get to the first century BC,
the first century AD,
Jewish communities and Jewish writers
are completely comfortable.
terrible, talking about gods in the plural and using that term to refer to angelic beings
of both good and bad sorts.
Right.
So the Melchizedek scroll and the Nancy scrolls talks about Melchizedek, who's this Messiah
figure coming with all the righteous gods.
Okay.
So I talk about the Olympians.
He's not talking about, right?
He's talking about the angelic beings, the holy ones of God, the righteous ones.
The only ones who have got this is total, totally comfortable,
verbiage for that. And it's worth noting that they're totally comfortable using this language
and talking about angelic beings in this way. Despite the fact that they are literally
surrounded by infested with and dominated by paganism.
Yeah, so no one had a sense of, oh, we can't say God.
because that would confuse people.
Yeah, the pagans will get the wrong idea.
Our people will get the wrong idea.
Right.
These same writers are constantly battling against, right?
Writing condemnations of the idolatry and paganism of their neighbors, the polytheism of their
neighbors against the Romans who are dominating them, right?
members of the Jewish community who had apostatized into Greco, Greek, and then Roman...
paganism. Right? The same people who are writing these condemnations don't have a problem with using
this language. Right? And this is important. Right? Because a big part of the problem surrounding
saints and patron saints is squeamishness about language. Yeah. And also like,
like, relatedly, what we might think.
of as a crowded spiritual world. Yeah, you know, but I've said before on the show, here's
another one of those shots. I don't think it's a shot. I think I think I know some of our
Protestant friends hear this as a shot, but I don't intend it as a shot. I intend it as more of
it all of French that I think functionally a lot of objections to things like this that come from
from our Protestant friends are based mostly on EBGBs.
Right. They're based on that language seems wrong. I'm uncomfortable with that language.
I'm uncomfortable with that practice based on their upbringing based on different things.
But it's not based on like, okay, I have a rational argument to pit against the argument
that you're about to make on Lord of Spirits about sex.
Yeah, and I mean this is one of the reasons why we try to focus so much on what the
Scripture says is because we know that we have many non-Orthodox Christians who are listening,
and this is one of the things that we all respect. We all respect the Scriptures if we're Christians.
You know, so that's why that's most of what we're doing. That's why I say this is the weirdest Bible study ever.
Yeah, and so if you look at this and you hear what we're saying, and we say, okay, yeah, like I understand the logic of that case,
I still have a mission about it.
That's okay.
It's okay.
Yeah, it's okay.
But we shouldn't make decisions about what to believe and how to be a Christian based on squeamishess.
Right? The squeamishess could be overcome. The heebie-gibies could be overcome over time. Right? If that's all it is. If it ends up being, that's all it is. Right?
But it's also very human and understandable to be a little squeamish. I have lots of people coming to the church who, whether it's the Theotokos or the Hibis,
that they are tacos.
saying or kissing eye comes wherever they're a little squeamish about it at first, right?
But I don't think that makes you a bad person and I'm not arguing that, right?
But I also don't think, again, that that should be the main obstacle to embracing truth,
or an obstacle to embracing truth.
Yeah.
And so, and, and, right, they were, as we're saying, for the biblical writers.
This wasn't even a concern.
Right, the fact that this could be misread or misinterpreted in some pagan way
Was not something they were deeply worried about
Not because they thought oh no one would ever get this wrong or twist this around right it was the exact opposite
Because they knew no matter what we write
No matter what we do, no matter what we say, people will as St. Peter says about St. Paul's
writings, twist them to their own destruction.
Right.
And in case there was any question about whether that was going to happen or possible, I present you the internet.
Yes. Right.
Which everything you say publicly will be turned to around a turn to destruction.
Right. Right.
So this is just a reality.
This is another one of those problems with having a text be the basis of something.
Yeah.
Is that text require interpretation
and they can be used as tools or weapons in any variety.
of ways by people who want to do so. But so again, we're pushing for what's behind the text. And so
what we're establishing here is that behind the texts, whether we're talking about second-templed
Jewish texts or we're talking about the texts of the Hebrew Scriptures, there is this robust belief
that in addition to the God who created everything, including creating the angelic powers and
and demonic powers. That there are an array of angelic
demonic powers, right, in the heavens and the underworld on the earth, right, and that these have a
particular role, particular roles in relationships with God and with human beings, right, such that they're
called holy ones, the good ones at least, the ones that actually are holy, and they're referred to even as
gods in the lower case.
So now we're going to bring back, again, we're digging in the crates in the old episodes,
but a great quote from Philo of Alexandria for a century BC Jewish writer who summarizes
this, he's commenting in this quote, he's commenting on Deuteronomy chapter four verse
19.
So we're going to hear Deuteronomy 419 first and then what Philo says about it and the
Yes.
Okay, so here's the Deuteronomy quote.
And beware, lest you raise your eyes to heaven.
And when you see the sun and the moon and the stars,
all the hosts of heaven, you be drawn away and bowed down to them
and served them, things that lured your God has allotted to all the
peoples under the whole heaven.
So that's the Deuteronomy quote.
And here's what Philo has to say about this.
And remember the basic rule everybody.
commentary is always longer than the original text.
So here's a file.
Some persons have conceived that the sun and the moon and the other stars are independent
gods, to whom they have attributed the causes of all things that exist.
But Moses was well aware that the world was created, and was like a very large city having
rulers and subjects in it.
The rulers being all the bodies which are in heaven, such as planets and fixed stars,
the subjects being all the natures beneath the moon.
hovering in the air and adjacent to the earth, but that the rulers of force are not independent
and absolute, but are the vice-royes of one supreme being the father of all,
in imitation of whom the administer with propriety and success the charge committed to their
care as he also presides over all things in strict accordance with justice and with law.
Others on the contrary, who have not discovered the supreme governor, who thus rules everything,
have attributed the causes of the different things which exist in the world to these subordinate
powers as if they had brought them to pass by their own independent act.
But the most sacred law-giver changes their ignorance into knowledge speaking in the following
manner.
Thou shalt not when thou seest the sun and the moon and the stars and all the host of heaven
be let astray and fall down and worship them.
With great felicity and propiety has he here called the reception of these bodies as gods
an error.
They who see that the different seasons of the year owe their existence to the advances
and retreats of the sun, in which periods also the generation of animals and plants and
fruits are perfected according to well-defined times, and who see also that the moon is
the servant and successor of the sun, taking care, taking that care and superintendents
of the world by night, which the sun takes by day, and also that the other stars, in
accordance with their sympathy with things on earth, labor continually and do 10,000
things which contribute to the duration of the existing state of things have been led into an
inextricable error, imagining that these bodies are the only gods. And then dot dot dot, so we're
skipping a little bit here. We must therefore look on all those bodies in the heaven, which the
outward sense regards as gods, not as independent rulers since they are assigned the work of lieutenants,
being by their intrinsic nature responsible to a higher power.
but by reason of their virtue not actually called to render in an account of their doings.
So that transcending all visible essence by means of our reason,
let us press forward the honor of that everlasting and invisible being who can be
comprehended and appreciated by the mind alone, who's not only the God of all gods,
whether appreciable only by the intellect or visible to the outward senses,
but is also the creator of them all.
And if anyone gives up the service due to the everlasting and uncreated
transferring it to any more modern and created being, let him be set down as mad and as liable to the charge of the greatest impiety.
And that's from his special laws. One, three, one of the things I note here is he, he both says, you shouldn't think of the heavenly bodies as gods and also odds, but they're under the one the most high God.
Yeah, they're not the only gods. Yeah, exactly
which if you remember, again, this is harkening back to our very earliest episodes. If you remember
that God, and its most basic sense and most ancient languages, means ruler, then you can understand
how he can both say they're not really Gus and they're only subordinate gods. In other words,
they're not actually the ones in charge, but they've been put in charge of some things by the one
who is in charge. That's what that means. And that's why there's even that phrase.
false gods in scripture like they're false rulers not that they don't exist. They're just not really in charge.
Right. And that's why we can say back to back that will own our God and among the gods there are none like unto me.
Yeah. Yeah. Right. Because it means ruler. Yeah. It means he's the only one that he said.
And then also, you know, frankly, the word gets used in a number of ways.
You know, but it's most basic senses.
makes Moses as a god to Pharaoh. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. So and and
Philo here uses a variation on the phrase, but God of God's is not
just an idiom. God of God's is also literal, right? That God
capital G, right? The true God is the God.
whom the God's lowercase G worship.
Right.
Um, and that's part of the argument against paganism, right?
Why are you worshiping them?
Shouldn't you be worshiping the one who they worship?
Yeah.
Uh, so right.
And so the, the, the picture here that Philo gives is of this sort of divine
Administration.
right and the sort of vast
Divine economy that includes all of creation and
That there are these spirits that are responsible for collective movement, right?
So he talks about the movements in the heavens, but also on earth, right? This is passing of the seasons
animals, right
the harmony of the whole order
Right that this happens through this administration. So I
I don't know.
So when we've used the term divine council, right, which by the way, let's be clear, let's
be clear.
Divine council is a comportment to squeamishness.
Okay.
We're actually talking about the council of the gods, but that'll flip some people out.
So divine council sounds less triggering.
Yeah.
Right.
But it means double and just means of God.
God's. God. Yes. Just an
out of the form, guys. The godly
assembly. Um, the so yeah. Um, I
don't know, but when we talk about
the Dubai Council, I don't know
how people picture that, right?
Because of course, we get a
picture of that in the
colon narratives of profits, right?
Because as we've said on the show,
the profit according to Jeremiah
is the one who has stood, right,
in the Divine Council.
I think sometimes, and based on that, the primary image that everybody thinks of, and it's
not a bad one, but I think sometimes the only image people think of is, oh, you have this
throne where Christ is, and then you have all these angels and saints kind of standing
around it all the time.
Yeah.
Like waiting for him to receive people, right?
Right.
Or waiting for him to interact with them.
Right
wrong. That is a biblical image. But remember, right, Angelic beings are vast cosmic
intelligences, right? They're actually doing things, right, in the cosmos, in the created
order. I mean, a royal court, there is a holding of court in which everybody is together
in the throne room. But a lot of what goes on in that court is the King saying, you go
do this, you go do this, you go do this. Right or
they're often there to report back on right to the king, right?
Yeah. Um, and of course, again, this is an image.
Right. This is an image. Um, God is not in one particular place, right?
Sitting on a literal material thrown somewhere with people at a certain
actual physical distance from that throw
Right? This is all an imagery and analogical language, right, to express reality to humans, right?
So, we also have to have this image that Philo is giving us, right, of the angelic beings who are
right, who are moving, right, the heavenly bodies and the cosmos, and involved with life on Earth,
Right.
nature and things flourishing and all of these things, right? The music of the spheres as it were.
Fear of fan of Aristotelian physics. All of this is happening. When we read St. Luke's Gospel here just a couple days ago,
Right, an angel appears to shepherd to the shepherds and then
the stars sing to them. That's literally what it's at.
Because that's what heavenly host means everybody. Yes. So we have to try and keep both of
these kind of images around. Right. So this isn't this isn't that like, okay, you know,
Clarence the Angel, you're in charge of...
serious major. So you just kind of keep an eye on it. Report back to me, if a
comment's going to hit a planet or something, right? When we say that angelic
beings are in charge of these things, we don't mean it in that kind of external
way. This is going to be important for where we're going in this episode. Yeah,
because they're not, they don't have material bodies. So they're, it's not like
your station at a spot.
right? Like watching or something. Yeah. Right. I mean, it gets in an iconography gets depicted
this way because how else do you depict? How do you being that has no material body, right?
Like you have to draw something, you know, right? But don't right. Don't
literalize that. But we have to be serious. And this is included in phyllo about the fact that in a
the way, right? The stars, right? These things in the heavens are their bodies.
in a way. Yes, right? In a sense. There what is animating them, right? And that's why you see an
iconography, the Sun, the Moon depicted as angelic beings. Yeah, right. And it's not a good, so
the spirit that we're talking about is what is animating and moving and ordering these things.
right this is what we mean
by them having this position in the administration, right?
Or being in charge of this thing.
We don't want to externalize the analogy too much, right?
It is.
Yeah.
It's not like a bureaucracy, right, where there's a department.
Astral body's department, Planetary body's department.
It's funny.
It's funny when, you know, when CS Lewis wants to depict hell, he depicts it as a bureaucracy.
Right.
It's like, OK, I'm on board with that.
What is in
is you go through time, the pictures of hell.
Yeah.
So yeah, it's not, there is this bureaucratic thing.
There's not like a department of, hey, Bob, you're
in charge of the pandas.
What's going on?
Like they're not mating.
Like can you do, you know, this is it?
Yeah.
Right.
This is it how to think about it.
It's also not a democracy.
Right.
This is part of what Philo is telling us.
Right? It is that all these folks get together and vote.
And God is like, well, I guess I got to go with you guys
on this one, right?
Yeah, that kind of council.
It's a royal council, not a...
Yes, right. There's a king.
There's a monarch.
All right.
The monarchy, right?
And he's not just the first principle of everything,
but, right, and so they are administering.
his justice and order and right.
And it's because of that that this isn't polytheism.
Yeah, we had a we had someone comments saying that he was a former Mormon and that polytheism
makes him feel extra squeamish which I hear you.
I hear you.
Yeah, but this is not polytheism because number one, you don't worship.
Like this is commandment zero in the Bible.
it gets repeated so much, don't worship those other beings. Right. Philo just said that. Right.
But it's also not polytheism because they're not independent actors. Yeah. Yeah. Right. They
aren't independent actors. Yeah. And I mean, it's worth noting, like let's look at some real
polytheism, right? Like the Greek gods. Some of them are children of other gods or whatever. Again,
that's not what's represented in a Christian tradition.
No, you know, angels and demons are not anyone's offspring,
anyone's, but also like one of the things that you see
in most of their most pagan traditions is that the gods
don't seem to be created with the exception of ones
that are like somebody's offspring.
They're just sort of there, you know.
Sometimes you get creations, but ultimately it's a group
of them that are all kind of there.
And you know what I'm saying?
And they're sort of a turtles all the way down kind
Yeah.
Yeah, and there's no one who is ultimately an absolutely in charge forever.
Like paganism doesn't tempt.
Yeah, yeah, paganism has a most high God, but he's not omnipotent.
Like omnipotence is not really a thing in paganism.
That is in the scriptures.
You know?
Right, right.
So just use, I mean people know the Greek mythology probably best.
Right. Yeah. Yeah. Right. Yeah. Zeus is the king of the gods. But you know, he's always
causing trouble. And then his wife goes behind his back to get all kinds of revenge all the time
and frustrate him and and mess with him. And the gods are always where his kids are always fighting
with each other. Yeah. And playing off against the other. This is a very different picture than
when we just read in filo.
Right, and that's at, at, at,
filo is deliberately differentiating.
The Jewish view from that and the differentiation is not that oh, we believe there's just one
God that exists and that's it.
Yeah, it's that we believe it a fundamentally different relationship between the true
God, right?
And the other powers that are his creation, right?
We believe it a fundamentally different relationship between them.
And we believe that who the true God is is fundamental.
different and of another kind than these other things that are called gods.
Yeah.
Such that he is the God who they worship.
Right.
Yep.
They are closer to us than they are to him.
Yeah, in terms of being created beings.
Yeah.
So the question is since he's absolutely omnipotent, omniscient, etc., etc.
Why bother having...
Why bother having anyone else?
That's a lot.
at all. Why? Right. And this is an important question because again,
this episode is really aimed to our Protestant friends, not to attack them,
or belittle them, or win an argument, but to try to help them understand
what this is about. Right. Yeah. And this is at the core of the question in some cases.
Well, God's in charge of everything. So just talk to him. Right.
right? Why do you need to go through anybody else? Yeah, like maybe I can because maybe there's
kind of a okay, well I can buy into this angel thing, divine council thing, like I guess
up yourocracy, right? But if it's a bureaucracy, you just go to the guy on top, right? Why
go through the middle management? Right? Just bypass all that, right? And so we have the
The core of this is the
again the reason why God does this because it's not out of necessity. Right. It's not that there's just some details that he's just too busy. Right. Or like he couldn't do without any God doesn't need to create anything.
doesn't need us, right?
Doesn't need the world, doesn't need,
there is zero necessity attached to this, right?
Zero, zero.
Let me repeat that, zero, right?
I know the...
This is, I know this is one of the things we harp out of this show is that God is absolutely free, right?
But this is where, honestly, this spot is where I think every place where some form of Christianity goes wrong goes wrong.
Hmm.
Is by having God not be ultimately completely free.
That's
point. It's different points and it's for different reasons, but at some point, you get to a point in
where theology goes bad because you impose some necessity on God. Right? So that's why I harp on
it so much on the show. But in this case, right? Again, there's no necessity. There's no necessity to
create anything at all to create full stop or to create anything or anyone in particular.
But God has chosen out of love to share his divine life, to share his divine nature, to
share himself with creatures.
And the beginning of that, of course, is creating them.
And then after creating them, it becomes sharing his life with them.
That's why.
And so the
There's a counsel, the gods of divine counsel, the reason why there is this administration, the reason why there are these
spiritual beings, right, who are charge of these things is out of God's love. He creates them and he shares
his life, his existence, his nature with them.
And so because of that we find, we find examples of this in the scriptures and different
places. We find that there are angelic beings who are assigned to elements of the natural order,
like the sun and moon and stars in Deuteronomy 419, or the devil having been referred to as the
the printed power of the air. We find this with reference to peoples, meaning people groups,
groups of people, tribes, cl-
you
hands later on nations have angelic beings are
spirits assigned to them. Think of Daniel, the Prince of Persia,
right, the Prince of Greece, St. Michael, who is Israel's
prince, right? And we find angelic beings assigned to
particular people. What we've come to call like guardian
angels, right? But who are assigned to
Check.
and guide individual people to read the book of Tobit with St. Rafael as an example, but this
is what you find the holy ones, the angelic beings, being assigned to all of these elements,
right? But these are three quick categorizations, right? Elements of the natural order, people groups,
and persons, right? Have these angelic beings assigned to them as guides, as shepherds, right?
And so that
That's sort of the state of affairs as we find it when we're talking about the Hebrew
Bible, the Old Testament, the created world, right?
And then of course, things happen.
Yeah, those things will happen in our second half.
That's right.
So we're going to go ahead and go to our first break and we'll be right back with the
Lord of Spirits podcast.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take your
calls on the next part of the Lord.
of spirits. Give them a call at 855-237-2346. That's 855-AF radio.
Is this world important to God or are His purposes entirely focused on a heavenly hereafter?
Do our physical experiences on Earth matter? Or are we just passing through?
Robin Phillips takes up these questions and more
in his new book, Rediscovering the Goodness of Creation.
From the beginning of creation, God has maintained a consistent plan for the earth
to bring this world to perfection under the loving stewardship of men and women.
The material world is not evil as the heresy of Nazism taught,
nor will the earth be destroyed as so much of modern Christianity teaches.
The Orthodox Christian hope is that this earth will one day be resurrected.
This manual for recovery.
to understand the God's purposes for the material world
and gives meaning to our present-day engagement with ecology, culture, art, worship, social justice, and asceticism.
Rediscovering the goodness of creation, a manual for recovering Gnostics, is now available at store.angianfaith.com.
That's store.angianfaith.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick.
and father Steven DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Hey, we're back.
Thanks a lot, boys, of Steve.
You know, that's one of the books
that you plug on this show every so often.
The one that we just heard the ad for.
I wrote a forward for it even.
You're starting to collect forwards, Father.
And well, some people, some people, you know,
based on a certain other forward I wrote,
I think I'd write it for anything.
But no.
What could that possibly be for?
It actually only books that I really believe in and Father Andrew's most recent book.
Thank you very much.
What category that's in real?
We will just leave to the reader.
So yeah, hey, we're back.
So yeah, we were in the first half we talked about Saints of the Old Testament, the Holy
one's the Old Testament, which that's the angels.
And we didn't mention it, but I wanted to give a little plug for the book of Jubilee's,
which does a whole lot of work in terms of talking about the creation of the angels and
then God assigning them to various elements of creation.
It's really beautiful and poetic, cool stuff worth reading.
Yes, yeah.
At some point, on our docket maybe soon, we may start doing some episodes about particular
texts like that.
That way saw the people.
we talk about the book of Inak all the time, but clearly do not listen to the podcast,
can have something to base that on. Yes, that one episode where we talk about the book of Inak
and then we'll go on to other books. Yeah. Yeah. I mean, we do quoted at the beginning of the show,
though. That's true. I mean, and the voice of Steve delivers it very beautifully.
Yes. So if you're one of those people who hears the show start and turns off ancient faith radio,
you think that's all we talk about.
Right.
Yeah, so yeah, so back into the crates the musty crates
Of the early episodes of this program
So one of our early episodes I don't know if it was the second or third or something
Was about the five ish falls of the angels. Yeah, I think that might have been episode three maybe
Okay
It's all a blur.
It is I mean and plus we were so much younger than yeah, it's true. It's true. I had about half this much gray in my beard
It shows taking a lot out of me anyway
So in that we talked about how you know we've we've
Milton has trained us all to think about this one primordial fall of the devil and the angels before the creation of the world
We won't be labor all that again to worry.
You can go back and listen to that.
Enjoy the technical difficulties.
By the way, I'll just break into that sentence here
and say we have an intriguing call.
Okay.
A Stephen from California, which that could describe you.
Yes, I am technically a Stephen from California.
Yes, so Stephen is calling or at least his phone is from California.
So Stephen, are you there?
I am here, fathers. Can you hear me?
Yes. We hear you. Welcome to the Lord of Spirits podcast.
Are you from Northern or Southern California?
And Northern.
Okay. That's a, that's a different state than I'm from. So yeah.
Are they talking about making it its own state at one point all the time?
Yeah.
Thanks. So yeah.
They want to make it in like five different states at one point. I think
Yeah, go for it you guys
I mean, I can do what they want.
Yeah, nobody wants San Diego. Come on.
All right, so what's on your mind, Steven,
from Northern California?
So I was wondering if it was possible to be a heretic,
but then become a saint.
Because I remember from an earlier episode,
you talked about,
an earlier episode you talked about.
I think it was constant team, the emperor,
and how he didn't have necessarily accurate ideas
about how God worked, but he's still considered a saint.
But then origin, if I understand this correctly,
is not considered a saint.
So I was wondering like what, how that works.
And I guess then how that works for all of us.
of us, like how right do you have to be if you have to be a certain percentage of right?
That's a great way to put it.
Well, you know, I'll say this, number one, being a heretic, I mean, I know that word gets
used in the number of ways, but in its technical sense, being a heretic means you have been
condemned by
appropriate authorities for not just thinking or just saying something that's wrong, but
teaching it, right? Like you are setting yourself up as a teacher of this heretical teaching,
right? Because I mean, you know, if you go to coffee hour in any Orthodox church and people
people start to discuss theology.
You're going to hear some heresies.
Like it's going to come.
out because people think all kinds of wrong things and they could sometimes they say them.
But that doesn't mean that they're teaching them. That doesn't mean that they're doing
that. And even if they are teaching it, maybe they just get corrected by their local
parish priest and there's no council that declares them heretic.
Right? So yeah, you can't, I mean, there is a certain sense in which you can accidentally
do a heresy, but like it's like saying, you know, uh, and.
a traitor to the United States of America, even though I've never been convicted of treason?
I mean, you could be, right? It's possible. You could be. But what really makes your traitor
is being convicted of treason, you know? So yeah, there's a certain amount of
juridical definition that comes along with that, where there's actually been someone that's examined
you and all of that stuff comes along. Is it possible to say wrong things and also to be a canonized
Yes, it is.
Witness every saint. Yeah, right. I mean everybody says something's wrong
You know and even sometimes they write it down. I mean we have saints who like they as I get later in their life
They say oh please
You know, please don't read the stuff that I wrote earlier
It's like they themselves admit that they said wrong things early on then might even be heretical in the sense of being a wrong teaching
so it's really
about how you end up and how you are
are assessed by the church, right?
Is what it comes down to being.
That's what I have to say about that.
I don't know if you've father Steven.
Yeah, well, so I don't think this is technically
it, I'm actually.
Okay, thank God.
But I didn't need another nod to my belt.
The year is almost over.
Right, well, yeah, it's, well,
the last decade of the year.
a couple things we have to...
this ambiguity, right? So we're talking about heresy and we're talking about
st.hood, right? And those two categories are not identical with saved and
and damned. Yeah. Right. Yeah. We have to clarify that first. Right.
Because if we're talking about soteriology, if we're talking about salvation,
the ideas in your head have nothing to do with salvation.
Yes, I mean every place that says in the scripture what God is going to judge people based on.
It's not the opinion post on X formerly known as Twitter.
Right. And as St. James tells us in his epistle, right, all the demons know there's one God.
Right?
They all know that Jesus Christ is His Son, right?
They all know that He died in Rose again.
They don't just think it.
They don't just, they know it for a fact.
That doesn't do him any good, right?
This is something that comes out of a certain form
of evangelical Protestantism, right?
This idea that the ideas in your head
decide whether you're a good person or a bad person.
This has recently been secularized as vocal liberalism.
which also believes that what makes you a good or a bad person is the ideas you have in your head.
What's the thing about it is there's no possible repentance.
And that dogmatic point of view.
Right.
So we're not talking about saints.
So part of the church glorifying someone as a saint is that the church is saying
This is a person to be emulated.
This is a person who shows us how to live the Christian life successfully.
The person being glorified as a saint, being on the calendar of the saints, is that this
person's life they lived in a certain way, such that it could serve as an example.
This is why you read what St. Forty is the Great said about St. Augustine, right?
St. Augustine is a saint, not because the Orthodox Church has embraced swaths of his theology,
but because of the confessions, because of the life he lived. Right? So you could be wrong about
a lot of things, because as we've talked about in the show, it's recently his last episode. Ideas
don't cause anything. You can have all kinds of wrong ideas and still live a beautiful life following
Christ. Yep. And I have all kinds of misunderstanding
and bad doctrine in your head, which is which probably describes most of the best people in most
parishes. And if you live your whole life that way, right, you're all for getting that, then that
person may very well become a saint, right? Usually in the Providence of God, if they wrote down any of
those mistaken things, they don't get preserved, right? That's sort of considered unworthy of the
the person and so.
they kind of die out over time.
St. Augustine was uniquely unfortunate in that regard.
I mean, the man St. Augustine wrote a whole book just
retracting things that he had published against his own will.
Everyone ignores it.
They still quote things he retracted authoritatively.
Well, St. Augustine said, it's like he retracted that.
Yeah.
So he hasn't gotten that benefit of history, but most saints do.
This is also a thing now with many modern saints that that process hasn't happened yet.
Yeah.
So you get a lot of quotes from 19th and 20th century saints that sound weird and wacky and that will probably be forgotten about 200 years for now.
Because they'll be considered unworthy of the person who they were.
And it's the person who they were that is the saint.
And then Heresy, right, the key thing to being a heretic, a heretic isn't someone who's wrong.
And Father Andrew was kind of getting at this, right? Arius is not a heretic because he was wrong.
We're all wrong to one degree or another about theology, right? Arius is a heretic because
He was wrong. His bishop came to him and told him he was wrong.
and he said, no, I'm right, you're wrong.
Yeah.
St. Alexander of Alexandria.
Yes.
And then a group of bishops came to him and said, you're wrong.
And he said, no, I'm right.
You all are wrong.
And then all the bishops of the church got together.
Pretty much all of them, a couple from Persia, right?
And then he said, areas, priest area,
Presbyter Aries, you are wrong.
And he said...
No, I'm right. All of you are wrong. Right. And that's what makes him a heretic and started his own churches dedicated is wrong teaching. You become a heretic not by being wrong, but by refusing correction.
Yeah, and by then setting out in your own pride and arrogance, right, to create your own alternate church structures, right, and this kind of thing. That's what makes your hair.
So...
No, a person like that, unless they repent, right?
If someone like that repented, right?
And humbly submitted themselves to the discipline and the order of the church,
they could become a saint, but then they would cease being a heretic, right?
By virtue of doing that.
Yep.
So as long as they're a heretic, as long as they're doing that, right?
that yeah, they're not going to be a say. Example that would be Tertulley.
Yeah, who became a modernist and left the church and that's why he's not a saint.
Yep.
So, does that answer your question, Steven from Northern California?
I believe so.
Thank you very much.
All right.
Awesome.
Thank you very much for calling.
So, good.
Yeah.
I mean, it's not...
It is relevant to what we're talking about.
That will become probably more apparent as we go.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, well, we can weave it in
Yeah, this is this is one of those cases where a lot of times we get calls on this show
It's for people who are actually tracking with us fairly well
So often to give a very direct answer to the question would spoil a bunch of stuff we're getting to down the line in the
Right, so we have to kind of answer it without completely answering it in a way that leads into where we're going
I'm masterfully done.
But so if I do say so myself.
Yes, right.
I did that with a lacquer.
So going back to that,
that ancient episode of your about the five-ish falls of the angels.
We talked about how Milton's wrong.
And wrong in a different way than most spirits or
in an additional way.
And how we see several discrete places in scripture that
were fall refer to angelic fault, what we might call angelic
faults.
This we're not going to rehash all that now, right, list them all
the five or so on all that, right.
But, um,
This has raised a bunch of questions, right?
And I think a lot of the questions we get concerning this
are generated primarily by that word fall.
And what that actually means, right?
Because for example, well, if the demons are fallen or Satan is fallen,
why do they still seem to be in charge of stuff?
Right?
Yeah, what is falling?
mean. Yeah. Or you know, like because Milton again, right, fallen means got thrown down into hell.
You know, some some people also use fallen to mean any turns to evil. Right. You know,
Right. The fallen is just a question of a moral turn. Yeah. Right. Um, yeah. So, so.
So what does this mean?
And I did when I thought it was a cute word play in the notes I gave Father Andrew, but
I won't burden you with that.
Because I think they would just complicate the issue more.
So you have, we'll get concrete with this.
So you have, we talked about
there are there were angelic beings right that were assigned to elements of the natural order to
peoples like people groups and to persons like people. What does it mean for an angelic being with one
of those quote unquote assignments right the spirit is playing the role of animating those things
What does it mean for them to fall?
Right. What is that sort of, I mean, we can't be super concrete with it, right? Like,
because it's not, we can't talk about it in material terms, right? But a little better
grasp of what that means. So, we've mentioned, for example, and I think the terms we used,
again, this may be part of the issue, right? Is, for example, the angelic beings who are
assigned to people groups.
like after the Tower of Babel event, right?
Deuteronomy 328 and all that that we've talked about before.
That they, in some cases, depending
like at like St. D and S.S. Theoreopogite,
all of them except for Israel didn't perform
their intended function.
All right.
All of the except for Israel fell.
And we talked about that in terms of acceptance.
worship from people and I think that language may be a little too external. Right?
Because I think that language plays into this view that like, okay, well this
adjelek being is like up in the sky somewhere and he's supposed to be kind of
overseeing them and they decide to start sacrificing cattle to him and he says,
Hey, this is cool. And so he starts telling them to do evil stuff
Right? Yeah. And that's not where we're going. Right? That's that's that's a
literal a little too concrete in the sense of being material. Right? Whereas we
may even have experienced. Right? So when we talked it when we've talked about
spirits, right? And spirits animating like a group of
people, right, or we could even extend this out to a tribal group or a nation,
or, right, how, sort of that collective spirit can kind of take a turn, right,
could kind of take a dark turn. And that's something that happens and includes the
people. Right, it includes the people taking this term.
to evil and to wickedness, right? But that it's not just, oh, each individual person who
was a member of the Amalakites, right? Each individual one decided to become a cannibalistic
fornicating murderer all at the same time independently, and it just they all did it, right?
Yeah, or, you know, to use a more modern example, every single person of the probably
thousands that belong to the Nazi Party.
to do Nazi things. Yes, there's all independently decided right at the same time they weren't all
compelled by some demonic, they weren't all collectively possessed and forced to do those things.
Right. Right. But that there is this shift to wickedness and to darkness. Right.
that's what we're talking about.
about when we talk about one of these beings falling is that shift to darkness. Do you
remember, Mother Andrew, which father it was who made that comment about the fall of the
devil and the animals? Oh, man, I know. It sounds like the kind of thing that St.
Ephraim, the Syrian would say, but I am not. Okay. I'm not going to tribute that to him
because I don't know offhand. So some people go digging in the crates of past
episodes and
Yeah, remind there's there's there is this idea that
Yeah, whoever said this
That and it's a speculation as I recall as I recall its speculations presented a speculation
Because hey, sometimes church fathers speculate just like humans knew
He says that say Paul does it at one point say Paul yeah, I don't have a word for the Lord of this
But here's what I think there's best. Here's my opinion. Yeah
Here's what I'm going to call the idea
that there's animal death and plant death in the garden of Eden, kind of, you know, as
the camera comes up on Adam and Eve, you've already got animal plant death because the
devil had been in charge of those that life. And so since he turns to evil, it brought
death to them first. Right. And so what's important to me about taking a quote here.
Yeah, is not, well, is that accurate or not?
Right.
Yeah.
But look at the way that that father in question
is thinking about the issue.
Yeah.
Right.
Even if he's just speculating it is wrong.
How is he thinking about the issue?
How is he thinking about the relationship
between the angelic power that becomes the devil
and the created order?
Right.
So something happens with this spirit
that is going...
guiding and producing the harmony of the created order.
And so that harmony is broken.
And so you have animals turning on and eating each other
and attacking each other, right?
You have, right?
This is the way of thinking.
I think it's important there
that that underlies this understanding
that we're trying to get across.
Right.
And so in one sense, right?
In one sense, when these angelical powers
spiritual.
powers rebel or fall or whatever language we want to use, this leaves these vacancies as
it were, right? In the divine economy, right? In this sort of administration, we were talking
about in the first half, right? And that there are not holy ones anymore in those positions
because they have fallen from what they were supposed to be doing.
At the same time, right, that they aren't vacancies in the sense that well all those demonic
powers now get thrown down to hell and don't have any influence or don't do anything.
Right.
Even though they're now fallen in the sense of being turned to evil of having left gods
and administration, having ceased to be creatures who are administering the will of God in his
creation and are instead doing the opposite.
are trying to bring about the destruction of God's creation. They are still
associated with the elements of the natural order or the peoples or the
persons, right? The people with whom they were previously associated. Yeah, right.
When the neighbors go bad, they're still your neighbors. So they are a function and
apart and a parcel of the disharmonie, the broken order.
the injustice within the created order that results from sin.
Right. So then, I'm actually going to do this in reverse order. So what were they called upon
to originally do? Right. Yeah, they're supposed to bring people towards God. That's the job.
Right, the language it's used for them for example.
book of Enoch that we talk about all the time. There referred to as shepherds. The 70
sons of God are referred to as the 70 shepherds in the animal apocalypse in the book of Enoch.
There's supposed to be shepherds. I think St. Dionysius uses this language too. They were
meant to shepherd.
the people groups, the people to God,
after the human fall back to God, right?
And so that this is, this was their purpose, right?
So, because we focused on the sun moon and stars
in the natural order at the beginning,
you might have gotten this idea of like,
you know, the modern sense of the clockwork universe
and their sort of right ghosts in the machine, right?
as people's and people too, right, with agency, right? Yeah. The the the natural order includes
animal life and plant life and right and and all of these things. So it's a more dynamic relationship
than that. Right? And so it was this this shepherding of bringing back into harmony, right? Bringing
back to God, right? Restoring order. That's that was their purpose, right? And
and they're guiding to a relationship that within the scriptures is alt-
decently defined by the idea of a covenant and that covenant is over and over again referred to as a marriage.
Right. Yeah. Like in Jose where yeah, where God in Israel is a kind of marriage is like the image that you see in Jose, right?
Particularly. But depending on where you are, it could be God in his creation as a whole.
Yeah. Right. It can be God and Israel as a people group.
It can be God and even an individual soul.
Yeah.
Right.
An individual, well not individual, but a person.
Because we don't have the idea of the individual yet.
Right. And that marriage is then expected to be chased
and often isn't on one side.
Right. It is on God's side.
but off on the other side.
isn't. Right? And so then in terms of understanding, again, the fallen demonic powers, we have to
understand that as the opposite of this, that they decide to shepherd humanity towards someone
and something else. Those who are being shepherded toward God become like God, those who are being
shepherded away become like the demonic powers.
And so there are these demonic shepherds.
right and because we like reading it and because people freak out when we read it and resort to special pleading
we're going to come back to the quote from St. John Crisostom.
Yes, this minor marginal humans.
Minor marginal church father that no one's ever heard of.
Yes, we never quote the church fathers on this show.
just as what? As I've heard, yes I've heard somewhere.
Yeah, say John Chris awesome. And for those of you who are new, we're being a little sarcastic.
He is a major, major, major church father and one of the greatest, actually, super important.
Yes. St. John Chris awesome. So this is from what's called four discourses chiefly on the
parable of the rich men and Lazarus. This is from discourse number two. You can look this up on
on the interwebs.
And that's not his title.
No. Right. Like these are he gave sermons people wrote them down. We found them. Right. That's
just descriptive. Right. We got four sermons. They seem to mainly be about the parable of rich
man and Lazarus. Yeah. Yeah. Cheafly. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Okay. So this is what he says.
For it is a fact that many of the lessons instructed think that the souls of those who die of
violent death become wandering spirits.
by that he means demons. But this is not so. I repeat it is not so. For not the souls
of those who die of violent death become demons, but rather the souls of those who live in sin.
Not that their nature has changed, but that in their desires they imitate the evil nature
of demons. Showing this very thing to the Jews, Christ said, ye are the children of the devil,
and that's a reference to John 744.
He said that...
they were the children of the devil, not because they were changed into a nature like
is, but because they performed actions like is, wherefore also he adds, for the lusts
of your father, you will do.
So this is exactly that relationship, you know, this sort of, you know, participation
with demonic forces making you like demons.
Right.
And so, and this is a parallel, right?
former Mormon friend.
Don't get triggered, right?
When we talk about theosis, when we talk about deification, the Orthodox Church, we are
not saying that there is a change of your human nature into something else, right?
You remain a human, but you become like God, right?
By participation in his works, right?
so that we can say God became man so that men might become God.
And this is directly parallel to what St. John Chrysostom says here.
Right. St. John Chrysostom is talking about a belief that still exists today, by the way,
right? The people who die, this sort of violent, horrible death come back and haunt the place
and kill all the kids on Elm Street. Right? Right. And he says, no, that's not it. That's
not how you become a demon. You become a demon by living like one. Right? Yeah. It's not
that you stop.
being a human and becoming an angelic being, right? That's fallen, right? But you become
like them, right? And so you can say that you become a, you can say that they become demons.
Yeah. And that's what St. John Chrysler was talking about when he quotes Christ there. Christ
is not saying, like, he's not saying all Jews for one thing. He's saying he's talking
to wicked people in front of him who are, who are happened to be Jews. He himself as a
his disciples are Jews, like it's not all Jews.
It's
That's the wicked people he's talking to.
That's why he's saying that they are, I think it's one other, you know, that they're
children of the devil because they do the work of their father.
Right.
Yeah.
Yes.
And it's, you know, not coincidental that it's the lust of their father, that they do,
Right, if the covenant into which we're shepherded by a jealous beings is...
compared to marriage, then this consorting with demons is always compared to
fornication. Yeah, right. It's always compared to fornication. We know that in many
cases, like with the giant glands, right, and pagan forms of worship, it literally
involved fornication, right? Right. But even when we're not talking about that
literal cultic fornication. It's still fornication.
in contrast to the marriage that is right returning to God.
Yeah.
So, this is sort of the state of affairs that comes into being.
Again, that we have in the Hebrew Bible in the Old Testament,
and then within the prophetic tradition
Contain there and there's
to be a solution to this. And this brings us back to Psalm 82 or 81 in the Greek, which we
sang on Holy Saturday as the Gospel hymn followed by a certain reading from the Gospel of
Saint Matthew that we're also going to talk about. You're the same kind of, again, not a coincidence
that these two things are brought together in a resurrection service.
That talks about literally the death of the gods.
God stands in the counsel of the gods and midst of them, he brings judgment.
Right?
He says, you were to administer the nations in justice.
You were to carry out these assignments.
You did the opposite.
You were wicked.
Right?
And you brought them to wickedness.
And so now you've been called gods and sons of the most high.
but now you will die like men.
Yeah, and I just want to add by the way because I know that there is
There is a also a reading of the Psalm which is you know perfectly valid as well
Which is that it's about
Human rulers who did not do what they were supposed to do I don't think that's a valid reading but anyway
He don't at all. No. Yeah, but I mean even if I can even if it like even if it is right like it it doesn't
And it doesn't matter because the point is the point that those who are set over.
others have not done what they're supposed to do and God is judging them, you know, because
of that, right? Even the, you know, but yeah, I mean, it's, to me, you can do both of those
readings at the same time and they can both be understood in correct way. Yeah. The problem
with the other reading is it kind of doesn't make sense with the details of the soul.
Right. Right. You have to what? Some parts and not others. What council of the gods is there
that God comes and stands in.
Right. He doesn't stand in the midst of it.
and he drew it.
Yeah, right, right, right.
Right. And like, yeah, they're gonna die like men,
they're men.
Like you would say, right?
So that reading just fundamentally doesn't make sense.
And that's not the reading Christ takes of it
in St. John's Gospel.
Well, I don't know if we want to go down
that rabbit trail right now.
We might need to do a dedicated episode I think.
Because I don't know for that one the whole episode
but yeah, or at least a part of it.
Somebody next college show we do,
So what do you call that about that?
I'll walk us through that because there we go. All right, you have to grossly
misunderstand St. John's gospel to not understand this is exactly how Christ is
interpreting it. But yeah, yeah, so no, see where I thought you were going to go is
Oh right, that you will often see the beginning of Psalm 82 or 81 quoted.
from quoted by church fathers and then they just make a general comment about
piosus. Right. Right. So a lot of a lot of what did
take John, Chris, I'm saying some of the less instructed. Yeah.
Therefore, say, oh, well, this soul is about piosus as if that solves an issue.
Right.
Because I don't even know what that would mean.
Because what?
The people who have undergone theosis are evil and God's going to kill them?
Yeah.
That doesn't make any sense.
Right.
We'll get back to that in a second.
The fathers are just short-handing this.
It's so well known that they're just short-handing it.
Right, you're supposed to understand.
and a whole dynamic here.
But so that's what happens.
And the Psalm ends with, there's another thing
that is incompatible with the other interpretation,
with a rhizogod and judge the earth
for that will inherit from all the nations.
Yeah.
Right.
Which refers to a fundamental that after this judgment
against the gods.
This then opens the way to God,
and the word inheritance is incredibly important.
Israel is God's inheritance.
This is the language that's used in Deuteronomy
when the nations are divided,
is that Yahweh chose Israel for his inheritance.
Right, so in this as it,
after the judgment of the gods,
now there is the shift in God is going to inherit
from all the nations.
not inherit all the nations.
But from all the nations, which is important, if we understand St. Paul, right, and what's
going on with him bringing Gentiles into Christianity.
Right.
So, there's this shift, right.
And as I mentioned, we sing this song as the gospel hymn on Holy Saturday as the lead
into us reading Matthew 28.
The end of Matthew 28.
The end of St. Matthew's Gospel.
when Christ, right before the ascension, says,
all authority in heaven and on earth has been given to me,
therefore go and make disciples of all nations.
Yeah.
And teaching them to observe all that have commanded you.
In other words, I'm in charge.
Yes.
And so the church has put those in parallel
to help us interpret this correctly.
Right.
That Christ has a-
accomplished what it prophesied.
The crisis judged the gods of the nations he now has all authority and
Because he has all authority now he is sending them out to all of those nations
Right in order to bring from all of those nations into gods inheritance
Israel
Right to become part of his people
Right.
But so now we have legitimate vacancies.
Yes.
There are some now since Christ has taken that authority back.
Right.
Those assignments are illegitimate.
And so Christ doesn't just say all authority in heaven and earth has now been given to me.
So all those angels are out of a job.
Yeah.
Right? But included there is the fact that he is now resharing out of love. Yeah, this is a renewal
of the divine counsel. Right. Because he now has all authority that they're going out to bring
these people in. And what is the destiny of those people going to be? The destiny of those people
is going to be the destiny of Abraham to become like the stars of heaven. Yeah. Right? And so we
we get this language of glorification, which is a-
Again, language of sharing in the divine life
and the life of the Holy Trinity and the life of God,
right, which is now shared with
the human creation in a special way,
because of the incarnation and death and resurrection
of Christ, the ascension of Christ, right?
And so the particular, when we look at the particular
metaphors, we get of this, what are they?
It's saying to the apostles,
You will sit on 12 thrones and judge the 12 tribes of Israel.
It's the 24 elders seated around the throne of God on their own thrones with their own
crowns that they cast down before God.
Yeah, and we should just reiterate here by the way that sitting on a throne and judging
does not mean like what we tend to think of like in a literal sense of like, oh, this
is what I think about this or this is what I think about that.
Right.
It's about being in command, you know, it's like sitting in the captain's chair.
Now, it's...
You're running something here.
Right.
It's the imagery that was used in the Old Testament
regarding the angelic beings now applied also to humans.
Yes.
And as we've commented before, it's not coincidental
that 24 with the 24 human elders is a third of 72.
Right.
So those vacancies,
those fallen angelic and easy spirits
are filled by humans.
Right who in a certain way become spirits
We'll get to that in a second and then we're not in a second and a little bit than the third half
um
and
so
Just like with the angelic beings
Right what would we expect what would we expect to find?
Based on this dynamic that plays out in scripture both in the Old Testament and then is fulfilled in Christ
Well, we would expect...
that the saints in glory, that human saints, human holy ones,
would expect that they would be assigned to elements of the natural order,
to peoples, like people groups, to persons, right?
We'd expect to find them doing the same thing.
Yeah, or in the words of Jesus, equal to the angels.
That they become equal to the
angels, right? So doing the same things, right? So the idea of
st.hood, not just the idea of being a holy person, but the idea of
st.hood as it's understood within the church, right? Is just part
in parcel of this understanding of redemption, this understanding
the bodyless powers of heaven. And this arc of the script
that we've just gone through. It's a natural result of it. Right? You can't sort of follow us up to here and then now say, Oh, but human saints and glory don't do any of those things. Yeah, they don't become equal to angels in any appreciable way.
Right. Yeah. Right. That's now somehow totally different. Yeah, I mean, you got to do something with Luke 2036 people.
I mean that
You know, I had big chunks of revelation.
Yeah, right.
Right.
You got to do something.
It's not just about like, oh, look how wonderful it is in the next life.
I think that's the way that it often is received.
Like, it's going to be great.
You know, but, but no, it's the language that's used is, is, is an active dynamic engagement,
you know, of what scenes are doing.
Right.
And, and what's taking place now.
Progressive friends.
I know many of you and you've heard from other people, right?
Other scholars, a lot of what we went through, right?
And then but then you get to this thing with the saints, the
hibi jibis said it.
It's like, I don't know, this is starting to get kind of Catholic.
I don't know what to do about this, right?
The hibi jibis are okay.
But again, shouldn't be an obstacle.
to accepting truth.
Yeah, right. You can get over the
HBGBs over time.
Right.
Um, and I don't see a way to break this arc
functionally. I don't even see a reason.
I don't see a reason to try to avoid it other than just this
discomfort.
Right. That's been sort of bred into many people.
Right. Um, which I understand the discomfort.
I appreciate the discomfort.
Great.
But again, you can't let your spiritual life be guided by comfort and discomfort.
That's that is a way that ends in disaster spiritually.
So a final note here.
We see one place where we see this manifested very early on in the New Testament
is St. Paul's reference.
to the Corinthians to baptism for the dead.
And we're going to make our, I was just saying we're going to make our ex-mormon friend a little
squeamish again. Yeah, I know. That poor guy.
That poor guy. Um, so we're the dead. We're just going to do this briefly. I think we've
talked about it on the show before we have. And you have a whole, a whole article on your blog about
it as well. There's our goal on my blog. There's a section, religiously apostles talking about it.
No.
But it's very clear when you dig into it,
when you look at how St. Paul uses V-dead,
as opposed to just dead without the article
that when St. Paul uses the article,
V-dead is referring to like V-dead in Christ,
that to departed Christians.
And the word that's used there for,
Right, baptism for the dead.
is not really in the place of it's more on behalf of or with benefit to.
Right.
And the idea here is that this is literally a patron relationship in the Roman sense.
Right. In the sense that there is someone in whose name you do things.
Primarily is an act of humility, right?
Such that the
on
for those things goes to the patron, right? You're the one doing the work, you're the one doing
the things, but you're patron, right? In aromains it would be sponsoring them and therefore receive
the glory for them, but in this sense it's sort of a voluntarily. So this is referring to the practice
of, which is obviously still an Orthodox practice today, of taking a saint's name at baptism.
So, right.
and this idea of a patron saint, right, that you then operate in their name.
So the folks who have, I have to as a side of, the folks who have criticized religion of the
apostles, particularly on this point, when I talk about the baptism of the dead, have brought me
no end of joy and laugh. It's great. Because for one thing,
They often say, well, where is he getting this?
Where is this coming from?
And if you actually go to the further reading bibliography,
the interreligionate apostles,
there are two journal articles specifically on this point
in there, right?
It's like the bibliography is invisible for some people, I think.
Yeah.
And if you go and read those two journal articles,
and the titles will, if you just read the bibliography,
like not read the books, just read the couple of pages,
You can tell
of the titles of these journal articles, exactly what they're talking about.
They're talking about baptism for the dead.
So if you go and read those articles, the footnotes have like everything that's
been written about this in the past, like, 100 years covered in there.
Okay. Um, so first of all, there's two sources there.
I also get, uh, which of the church fathers say this?
And if you, if you go and look this up, say in your ancient Christian commentary on
scripture, what you'll find is they don't comment on it.
Yeah, there's one sort of little known church brother who comments on it and just kind of says,
I don't know what this means, right?
Yeah.
And then everybody else doesn't comment at all.
So St. John Chrysostom just passes over this whole baptism for the dead thing like it's
not even there.
Yeah.
Let me suggest to you, why would all of these well known church fathers just pass over it
like it's nothing weird when it's so weird does?
because it wasn't weird to them, maybe because they knew what it was.
talking about. And then third, and then I'll be done with this little mini rant. I promise.
Third, my favorite is when they accuse me of novelty. So like I literally argue that an Orthodox
church practice is apostolic and they tell me that's novelty.
over this late day and argue that this practice is apostolic.
It's amazing. Less relevant to my own personal enjoyment of my critics.
And I really need a better class of them. But
the more pertinent and more important,
Once we understand this idea from very early on,
of patron saints. This also helps us understand the phenomenon of pseudopigraphy,
both in Second Temple Judaism and in early Christianity. That is writing in someone else's name,
chiefly a saint's name. So, friend of the show, Barterman, has his book forged.
These New Testament books aren't written by who you think they were written by.
Which is amazing, because it's like, you know, this wasn't really written by Saint Mark.
It's like, what is Saint Mark known for other than writing?
The guy, why would Mark?
Why would you attribute something to him?
I mean, let's just call the guy who wrote it Mark.
Like, okay, Mark, like, I mean, the reason why people might plagiarize
is
were forged up today is because like there's royalties at stake, you know, right?
You make money, you make money off of selling books, right?
That's a thing.
But in the ancient world, that was not a thing.
Right.
Yeah.
So the idea was, right, among amongst the vast swath of student
Now there are things that go on, right?
There are no stick texts where the reason they're being attributed to some apostles that they're trying to claim Jesus actually taught this.
Right. So there is some of that. It's not that that doesn't exist.
Right.
But in many cases at least.
Right. What you actually have is something similar to this patronage situation.
And especially with someone who is.
under the authority of someone else.
So, for example, we're told in the book of Isaiah,
that Isaiah's prophecies were written down and then later collected by his disciples.
Yeah.
And this causes a really simple solution to this whole second and third Isaiah thing.
Right?
Because there are sort of differences at the places where they draw the line.
right? And it's like, okay, yeah. So there were three different collections of Isaiah's prophecies
and they all got put together into one big one. You can't sell book with simple solutions though,
really. In the modern day. Journalism has to be written. Or I thought I was going to get a ton
of controversy when the whole council of God episodes about Second Peter came out. And I didn't,
at least as far as I could tell.
I don't know if I'm happy or not.
Man, it's because they email me all the complaints.
That could be it.
Did you get any?
I don't remember.
Oh, I just delete emails that refer to you now.
Oh, okay.
Well, that's probably sound practice.
You probably set up a junk filter just if my name's in it.
There we go.
But that it looks for all the world.
like second Peter was compiled from St. Peter's preaching.
and teachings by after his death by some of his disciples.
Right.
And that explains a whole bunch of things related to St. Jude's epistle too that I won't go and do
here. Right? Or the possibility, the pot, and folks, I said possibility, the possibility
that it was someone other than the first century St. Dionysus the area opa guy who wrote
The works attributed to St. Dionysus the area.
a guy, right? A person could have taken St. Dionysius's name at baptism or as a
monastic and be writing in his name and not be lying. We're trying to defraud
anyone but rather have this patron relationship where he wants the credit to
go to his patron saint and not to him. Self. Right? He was writing. So if he was
written in the second or third century, right? By someone else that attributed
Yep.
It's not a case of lying that doesn't discredit the contents, right?
Those are all presuppositions because a lot of pseudopigraphy at least, a lot of this writing
in someone else's name was founded on this principle, right, of giving the honor and the
credit to to someone else, making oneself a ghost writer, right, so that someone else
would get the credit, right, which has a certain asceticism and humility to it that few
today with.
practice. Alright, well, that wraps up the second half of this episode of Lord of
Spirits. We're going to go ahead and take our second and final break and we'll be
right back. Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and Father Steven DeYoung will be back in a
moment to take your calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits. Give them a
call at 855-237-2346. That's 855-AF.
Radio.
What are we to make of the unseen world and spiritual warfare?
The Lord of Spirits, book version, is now available at store.ancientfaith.com
written by Father Andrew Stephen Damick.
To the modern mind, dragons and demons are just the inner demons of psychology.
And angels are often reduced to...
to the better angels of our nature,
that is to our better human impulses and virtues.
Talk of spirits is really about psychology.
But to the ancient mind of millennia ago,
even up to the pre-modern mind of just centuries ago,
these are real beings with personal presence
who inhabit our world and affect us.
Father Andrew provides a distillation and explanation
of the material in the popular podcast.
the Lord of Spirit, which he co-hosts with Father Stephen DeYoung.
Get this brand new book today at store.ancientfaith.com.
That's store.ancientfaith.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits,
the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
Welcome back everyone. We just got a note from a listener in Australia. So welcome Australia. We're glad to have you on board.
And, uh, hey, nice to hear that plug for the book. How are they listening to us? Is it unlike a CB radio in their web?
I don't know. There's this thing called the internet. It's crazy, man. Right. But I mean, I'm pretty sure the nuclear war took that out in Australia.
based on the documentaries I've seen about life there.
I mean, I have been
told that every living thing there is actively trying to kill any humans that come around.
You have the mutants of the wasteland, right?
It's the reason why my wife will never come with me to Australia because she's like,
I don't want to be.
And on top of that, Australians have also added something called the drop bear.
Look this up, people.
I'm not kidding about this.
The drop bear, and I think the drop bear legend is designed to prevent anyone from
from coming to Australia.
Like it's not, like it was not put together
by the Australian tourism board.
We'll just put it that way.
So drop bears.
I have to say, people don't realize how much
of a humanitarian huge act man is.
I go to go to that wasteland,
and go into the battered shell of a theater
and perform musicals for them.
Like, oh, it's not there though.
But here
escaped and he goes back and he goes back. Oh wow. Yeah. Yeah.
They're all hard to come back. Well, come tonight on stop.
It's the third half. He's almost a patron saint of Australia, almost
with a love and care. He shows to his people.
That's not where I thought the beginning of this half was going to go. But,
but there we go. We just had to go in here from an Australian.
If you Jackman is listening
go ahead and call in and give us.
Please.
You.
We want to hear from you.
Hey, you get off of that cloud.
Anyway.
Whew.
All right.
Needed more musical references.
Sorry.
I don't don't get me started.
I can reference music.
So yeah.
So we dipped our...
toes in the last half into this a little bit. And now we're going to sort of dive into the deep end of this.
And that is so concretely pulling in some stuff we've talked about before. What is a spirit? How does a spirit work? How does a spirit relate to those in that of which it is a spirit? Right.
And hopefully on the way we're going to see this is another area where we get a lot of questions
Right? Yeah. And because this is hard to understand. Yes. Well, what we're pushing at here,
and already this episode, but now especially here, as we come, you know, toward its climax,
meaning it's latter. Nice. This is this is stuff that we're pushing at like at the edge of what
humans can understand. Yeah right and we're not claiming we under
stand. Right. Right. So this is and you know, since we're playing the hits tonight from
way back, right? Part of the problem is that the way we tend to approach this issue, what
is a spirit, especially since we're thinking about the spirits of the righteous made perfect.
we're thinking about saying.
right? We're thinking about human saints and glory is that when we approach it, we're
approaching it from the idea from the angle of what is it like to be a spirit? Right? Yeah.
What is it like to be that? What will it be like? Right? If I if when I die, I'm in that
number when the saints go marching in right. Oh man that brings me back.
Shout out to Louisiana.
Anyway.
Right.
We're thinking about what's that going to be like, right?
Is really sort of part of our thinking on that.
And as is our want, don't know what it's like to be a bat.
Right.
We can't know what it's like to be a bat,
which is below us in the created order.
Let alone...
understanding what it's like to be an angel or a glorified human which is
above us in the created order still created but above us in the created order
above us in terms of the level of consciousness that we're talking about.
Right. So we can't approach this from what is it like to be a spirit? We have to
approach this from, what does it mean to be a spirit?
Yeah, and saying what
something mean is fundamentally about how we relate to it. Right. Right. So we can say what it
means to be a bat by giving a bunch of descriptors of bats and how they relate to humans and other
creatures. Because it means like everything that means means something to us. Like that's what
the meaning is. Right. Can I say what it's like to be a bat? We're going to say what it means to be
a bad. But it means to be a bad is to be a mammal.
with webbed hands essentially that form wings that allow for flight, etc etc etc etc etc.
That's assessing what we mean when we say bat, essentially ultimately.
It's what do we mean when we say bat? When we say that is a bat, what do we mean?
And so when we say that is a spirit, where we say he makes his angels' spirits.
What do we mean by that word? Right?
And we've talked before, again, related to the bat, that there are different levels of consciousness
that until very recently, and by very recently, I mean, until the 20th century for the most part,
the idea of consciousness was seen as a very binary thing as zero or a one.
Yeah, humans have it. Nothing else does. Well, maybe yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah, right, right.
But not animals.
Right.
Consciousness was seen as some kind of self awareness
or something that, or something to do with language
or something to, right, that animals don't have.
Right.
So, Hagle, and he's gonna show up again later.
Hagle animals are just basically little machines.
They're not aware in any real sense, right?
19th even early 20th century people buy and large
don't think animals really feel pain or at least the way humans do because they're not conscious.
Right. You get a lot of scientific experiments going on at that time that now we find a
porate, right? But we now understand obviously for a variety of reasons that that's not accurate,
right? Yeah. That animals, for example, have different kinds of consciousness and different levels
of consciousness, right?
And we understand that even plants have, as organisms, have some kind of rudimentary
level of consciousness, right?
They've played the sounds of water near plants and the roots of the plant will start to
grow toward the sound.
I know.
And it's so weird.
Yeah.
So there is something that is processing input from the environment.
and acting upon it in some way, right?
That's some level of consciousness, right?
And then we've even talked about how
what once we go below the level of organisms,
one of the first things we notice
is that actually the things we think of as organisms
like animals and plants and humans
are actually not a single system,
not a single.
organism, but are made up of other independent organisms.
Yeah, which sometimes interact with systems in other or in other larger organisms.
Weirdly enough. Right. Right. Like Father Andrew loves when I bring up how our gut flora
chemically communicate with the gut flora of other people around us. Never sit next to me again.
time. My gut flora are fascinating. I think they're mainly made.
of McDonald's hamburger buns. But anyway.
And Ed Licker, sadly. But anyway.
So, right, so it's not just that any given organism is a system,
it's a collection of systems.
And as we just said, some of those subsystems communicate
with the environment and
And so.
Some of them are self-guided in self-processing, right, within the whole, right?
And so the consciousness that we ascribed to the organism is really an overarching consciousness
of the sort of mini rudimentary, right?
Like my gut flora may have the level of consciousness of like a plant, right?
rudimentary consciousness.
But that's still part of my overall consciousness, right?
And what do I mean by that?
Well, trust me, the state of your gut floor
I can affect your mood.
Oh, yeah.
Right?
Read some of St. Gregory the Thaloid Jins poetry
when he was having stomach troubles.
He writes about it very candidly.
There's a good argument to be made
that the reformation happens because of gut floor.
I mean, that's well known.
It's well known.
Right and so
The end result is that there is
There is some level of consciousness that arises
Out of any ordered system that transmits and or processes
information
Right now by some level of consciousness again, right
Think about the plants
Think about very simple animals or things like seeing
that are somewhere in between, right?
We're not saying they all have human consciousnesses, right?
We're not saying like I am going to go and speak to the earth
because plate tectonics is an ordered system.
Find out what the earth wants, right?
That's not what we're saying.
Right?
It's a, we're talking about rudimentary levels of consciousness.
But they're there.
And so once we understand that,
that there are these levels of consciousness below.
the level of human consciousness. There's no reason for anyone, and now I'm speaking outside of even religious terms.
There's no reason for anyone, of any religion or no religion at all, to reject the idea that there could be conscious levels of consciousness above humans, above an individual human person.
Right, there's no reason for that.
Now.
Christianity teaches us certain things about those levels of consciousness, right?
Spiritual beings and genomic beings, right?
The Saints and glory, everything we've been talking about this episode.
But even on a purely materialist basis, there's no logical reason to exclude the possibility
of those things existing, right?
In some sense, in some form, right?
So there's this higher level consciousness.
And so...
So as the examples we were giving before, right, you have a people group that people group
has a collective spirit, right?
There's this collective consciousness of the whole that is not just the sum of the parts,
right?
It's a kind of democratic way or something, right?
Let people move and do things as groups, not solely as individuals.
As the examples we gave in the last half,
this is neither being forced by a spirit
to do something,
nor just all of these individual persons
all making the same exact choices,
bad choices, or good choices, all at the same time.
Right, unguided by anything.
So when we've talked about this in the past.
Right? We've talked about spirits in this sense in the past, right? As guiding the spirits
who are assigned to elements of the natural order to people, groups to persons. One of the
main questions we've gotten is, well, does that mean that these spirits sort of like come
into existence and cease to exist or they get assigned and reassigned. Right, like...
was there a spirit of like the Prussian people? Is there there's no more Prussia? Are are agregors real?
Yeah. Um, there's an idea to they sort of spring into being, do they? When some new, right,
you know, like the United States of America didn't exist and then it did.
All right, just so it is like this news is a new angel born or get its wings or something.
Right? That's now like assigned to it or the spirit that's moving the people.
So.
And ultimately that's the question of do spirits come into existence?
Yeah. And the answer to that depends on how we define existence.
Right. And I don't mean what your definition of is is.
But what it means to come into existence. So the way we usually use that,
that way I think.
it's being used in the question, at least most of the time, is it's being used come into
existence as in ex-Neholo, right? Like previously, there was nothing. Now there is a thing.
Yeah, right in the universe. And that idea, that that temporal transition,
Right between
there's this second in time and this place in space that is empty and then that in another moment of time
that space is filled with something, right? You can see there's a problem with applying that to a spirit
Because a spirit doesn't have material existence.
that occupy a space and time.
Right?
So, if you meet existence in terms of material reality, material existence, do spirits come
into material existence?
Well, no.
Sort of, definitionally.
Yeah. Right.
But, we have to go back to the five-ish falls.
A little bit here.
And we have to learn, I'm suddenly reminded of the original
back to the future movie where Doc Brown says to Marty,
you have to think fourth dimensionally.
That's how we're saying here, but you have to learn
to look phenomenologically.
Phenomenologically.
So we talked about, right?
We have these five, four, maybe five,
that's why five ish.
point right in
What would be described as human history?
We're not going to get it.
We've other episodes we've talked about what sense of history we're talking about with
the scriptures, but in scripture, at these five points in human existence, there are
points where angelic beings are said to fall and we talked about what that means in the
last half.
Right?
And so one of the questions we get then is like,
How does that mean, you know, the day before the angel was a good angel doing its thing,
and then that day evil.
And we've tried in various ways to make the point like no, because see there you're assuming
an angel is like a human.
You're assuming what it's like to be an angel.
Right?
because they don't have material bodies experience time and space differently than we do.
And we don't know how differently because we don't know what it's like to be an angel,
but we know it's different than the way that we as beings with material bodies experience time and space.
Right? But what we're saying when those things are attached to those point in time is that that's when
the change the fall, right?
the shift, however we want to describe it. That's when that shift or change or fall
enters into the experience of humanity, the collective experience of humanity.
Yeah, we had we had somebody actually ask on in the YouTube chat. Essentially
is it the case that every time an angel falls that there's some kind of effect
in the world and my response to him was how would we know if they're...
was a fall without one.
We wouldn't know.
Like we're not given some book of objective knowledge
of things that has no relation to us.
Because it's the effect in the world
that is written about in scripture.
Yeah.
It's the effect in the human, the world of humanity.
And that's why, as Father Andrew said,
we have to think phenomenologically.
Not in terms of metaphysics,
in terms of being, in terms of an esoteric sense.
right? Forget Plato. Right? We're talking in terms of human experience. Right? And so the place where
humans began to experience this fracturing of humanity, of the spirits of the different nations,
leading them not toward God but away, setting them against to each other. They started to experience,
human started to experience that after the tower of BAM.
Right. And so that's when it gets written about. Right. The humans experienced the failed rebellion of
the devil against God in Genesis 3 in the Garden of Eden at the expulsion from Paradise. That's where
that entered into the realm of human experience. How the devil himself experienced that we can't know.
Let alone how God
I'm not an expert.
Right, right, right.
Right, like you can even talk about God experiencing things.
What that, right?
Like that's beyond any kind of knowledge.
But that's when human right,
that's when it errors into the human world.
Right?
And so if I come into existence,
you mean come into human experience, right?
Come into the world of humans,
Ben.
Yes, then yes, there is a spirit that comes into existence at such a point at the founding
or forming of a nation. Yeah. But spirit again is is a phenomenological term. Right. It's about
relation between beings, right? Experiences. Yes. Spirit here is yes is a phenomenological term.
it is right and that's how it's you
he makes his angel spirits. He makes them to be spirits. He puts them into this
relationship. Right. He being God. Right. So yes. And so and so the saints of glory are made
spirits in this sense. Right? So what then is
We've hinted around this, we've we've poked around this.
We've kind of said what it's not. What is the relationship between a spirit and a person or a spirit and a people group or group, right?
Or a spirit and some elements of the natural world. The word that's used
to describe this in Scripture and of the fathers is Kenania.
I'm not sure if you're gonna
offend the Greek swath or Andrew.
I would say or like the
pronounced at the evangelical way.
Early 80s CCM.
Three-plug your ears.
Band.
Coinonia.
Actually I think they said Coinonia.
Oh man.
Rives with Narnia.
So I didn't do that Greek people.
It's not the way I would normally say it, but...
said you're a raspy and hate male to father.
Yeah, I don't normally do that.
That's me.
So yeah, and in those circles where that father
Andrew was referring to where that term was used to got
really watered down to mean like fellowship, like coffee
hour.
But this is a much more important term in classical Greek.
For example,
It's used, this is the term Plato uses to describe the relationship between the forms and things.
Participation, to take part in. Right. That's how it's often translated.
This is the term that St. Paul uses when he says, you know, what the nation sacrificed,
they sacrificed to demons and not to God.
I...
do not you want you to become Kenania.
I do not want you to become participants with demons.
Yeah, right.
So this describes a potential relationship
you can have with demons for St. Paul
brought about in part at least through pagan sacrifice, right?
It also in the same passage,
St. Paul uses the same term to refer to relationships.
that can be had with God, right? But points out you can't have this relationship with both God
and demons at the same time. Yeah, one of the other. Right, one of the other. This participation.
And what this participation is pointing to is an aligning of wills, right? Meaning it's voluntary
the original sense. Right.
And a lining of wills that then brings about an aligning of activities, right, meaning energies,
sin or gay, sin or g, right, there's a synergistic relationship that is being talked about here.
And so one can, through the Spirit of God, through the Holy Spirit, have this kind of
synergistic relationship with God in which we align our will with God's will.
We through our activity
participate in his activities, grace, the energies, the divine energies, right?
What God is doing in the world, we participate in that. We align our will with his.
This is the path of theosis where we become like God, right? The other option is
that we align our wills with a demonic spirit. We align our wills, we align our
activities and then the same result that's synergy
results in, is Saint John talked about us becoming like the demons, right, and
brings about our destruction. But so this is, this participation works in both
directions, right, both top down and bottom up. As we said, it's not just top
down. It's not that the spirit comes and possesses a group of people, right?
For example, it forces them to do things against their will and puppets them,
Right.
God doesn't do that. Holy Spirit doesn't do that on the one side. Demons don't do that on the other side.
The language we get is shepherding, guiding, etc.
On the other hand, it's not just bottom up. It's not just the sum of the parts.
Right, right.
Theosis doesn't happen.
Sorry, Pallegis, by human efforts.
Right.
Ah, this...
This isn't something that just we do on way or the other where we are completely,
completely free, moral, so it is going in both directions.
It is actual synergy.
And we use still sometimes the word spirit in this kind of synergistic sense.
Right.
So the time of year it is people talk about the spirit of Christmas.
You need to get with the spirit of Christmas.
with being a sour...
push right. Yeah. Or do you have school spirit? Wait a you know, it's clear that school spirit
is not just a bunch of individual people cheering for the football team. Like there's something
more going on there. You know, there's a sense of everyone belonging to the same thing.
Right. And being on the same page, they're being some guiding that there is a school spirit.
that is guiding everyone.
and bringing everyone together, right? Or the zeitgeist, right? The spirit of the age.
You who marries himself to the spirit of the age soon finds himself a widower,
basic truth. But you can wed yourself to the spirit of the age. Right. Notice the language.
There. Yeah, yeah, a wedding. Yeah. And this kind of understanding of spirit, by the way,
This kind of understanding of spirit by the way is key to understanding what we mean by holy tradition in the Orthodox Church
Yeah, and we've talked about this before a bunch right that you know what we don't mean by tradition in the Orthodox Church is a
Bunch of secret stuff that the bishops have handed down at their
Consecrations that they don't tell anybody
that we claim goes back to the Apostles.
The
So, Terrick. Yeah, oral tradition. Read some senior and ass. Right. You'll fix you up on that one.
Well, and this is why like there's a famous line. I think it's on on the incarnation where
St. Athanasius says that unless you're living, unless you're imitating the life of the saints,
and obviously that's pointing at the way you live, unless you're imitating the life of your
you can understand their teachings.
Yeah.
You know...
which is you have to align your will with this,
with the Holy Tradition.
And it's not just a big list of things that you get right,
like a quiz that you get all the answers right.
Right, so yeah, so we talk about Holy Tradition
in the Orthodox Church as being the life
of the Holy Spirit in the church.
Yeah, right.
And that sounds fancy and, oh yeah.
But what does it mean?
Right? It means that we look back at the church's history.
And we see that there are places where humans were synergizing, were in sync, where their
wills were aligned, where their activities were aligned with the Holy Spirit, with what
God was doing in the world. Right? That they're being guided by the Holy Spirit. They were
speaking but they were being guided by the Holy Spirit.
Right where this synergy was happening.
Right. And we point at those places and we say,
these places are authoritative for us in the sense that these
places in history serve as guides for us as we seek to do the
same thing.
Right. As we seek to do the same thing.
So the ecumenical councils, right, certain writings of certain
church fathers, because wherever we don't have all of them,
We don't have writings of all the church fathers.
We could potentially be considered church fathers.
We don't have all the writings of any given church father.
Right?
We have the ones that have come down to us through tradition.
The copying of the scriptures.
Right?
Now do they just the canon of scripture, etc.
etc.
These are all places where humans were synergizing with the Holy Spirit.
and so that fact and that recognition
from us means that they're authoritative and guiding us to do the same.
Right? As we continue this historical journey of the church.
And so there is a sense in which it is true to say that holy tradition is the Holy Spirit incarnate as history.
Yeah, that is an absolute though people as I say that
There are a certain number of the more instructed who probably blanched because they heard shades or the shade of George William Frederick
Kagle. Right. When I said that. And there's a ghost that haunts a lot of people. And so the reason I said in a sense is that when we see
say that, right? We don't mean what Hegel meant when he said similar things. Okay? So,
Hegel, when Hegel talks about spirit, Hegel is actually very clear. He means the Holy
Spirit. Hegel was a Lutheran. And if you don't understand that Hegel is a Lutheran, self
described, he always insisted he was an Orthodox Lutheran. And if you don't understand that
He's a Lutheran, you won't understand Hagelcrick.
because he's really Lutheran. But he means the Holy Spirit, but, but,
Hagle worked in the opposite direction. Hagle understood history is having a
through line and Hagle is vastly influential late 19th throughout the 20th century
All right, we have to...
theology and philosophy, just about everything, right?
History has this through line.
It's going somewhere.
It's progressing in a direction.
Of course, 19th century, Germany and 19th century,
German Lutheran, we're the peak of that.
At least for that point, right?
He didn't think it out.
It was going to be a valley, right?
He didn't think history was at an end, but they were the peak then.
I'm sorry.
So, but that meant that whatever unfolds for him, whatever unfolds in history, the unfolding
of history was the unfolding of the Holy Spirit and therefore the unfolding of God.
Yeah.
So, you know, the times equals the work of the Holy Spirit.
Right.
So he could, having helped found the University of Berlin.
see Napoleon there in person wrecking the place and say there goes history.
See Napoleon is history incarnate because he was the one shaping what was going
to come next for Europe.
Hagel saw. Yeah. Which meant for Hagel that he was being guided by the Holy Spirit.
Right.
Ooh.
Yeah.
which is not what we're saying. We do, however, as Orthodox Christians believe that the history of the Church is going somewhere.
Yes.
Right. We don't believe that any given generation is the peak of it.
Despite how sometimes you hear some Orthodox Christians talk, as if the fourth century was the De Numah.
at least much better than now.
But we look through the history of the church to find these places that are authentically
part of Holy Tradition.
We look through the writings, we look through to find these places that constitute genuine
parts of Holy Tradition, and we reject other places.
There are more robber councils than ecumenical councils.
And there are a lot of bishops and even patriarchs who aren't saints.
Yeah, most of them.
Yes, actually.
Most of them.
And emperors, you have an even worse batting average.
Yeah.
Right.
So we, we identified these particulars as being places where
people are synthesizing with the Holy Spirit.
Particular people places, writings, events.
Right.
We don't take the sweep as being on
automatically inspired. But the reason I wanted to spend a minute on this, right?
The Hegel is, I think most people now, at least in the circles of people who listen
to this show, right? Or at least who aren't hate listening to this show. I don't think
people fundamentally understand how liberal theology works, right? And this can give us a
window into how the
liberal theology works. Liberal theology is in keeping with
Hagle. The Hagle, we're rejecting on this show just to be
clear, right? Not promoting liberal theology, but we need to
understand liberal theology now works. And the reason I'm just
saying liberal theology, right, I'm not saying liberal as
opposed to conservative. I'm saying liberal in the sense of
Post-enlightenment.
That doesn't think the Enlightenment...
was a bad thing. Right? I'm not
got post enlightenment theology. I'm
talking about, well, let's get to
brass tax liberal theology what it
does. And I'm not identifying this.
I'm not talking about liberal
Protestantism or Catholicism or even
orthodoxy because there are people
in all of those groups. I think
fewer of them in orthodoxy than
the other two right now. I don't
no but
proportionally with Roman Catholicism. Liberal Protestantism is certainly the biggest liberal
theological movement, but there are a lot of liberal Catholics, but the Roman Catholic church
is awful big, so I don't know percentages. They're relatively few, but there are some
within the Orthodox church, and there are of course people doing liberal theology stuff who don't
identify with any of those and whatever, right? But liberal the
essentially like Hegel takes whatever point in time they stand at as being the apex of history to that point.
This means I've critiqued it this way on the show before but I'm going to do it again.
This means that liberal theology is always innately.
nately, chauvinist, at least somewhat racist, colonial, right? Because again, you have to take
your culture and civilization as being the apex. So he's the other ones who might disagree with you
are somehow primitive, backward, unenlightened, etc. Right? So there's all
always overtones of that. Right? Always overtones of that within liberal theology. But you take your
point as being the apex of history to that point and you ascribe the developments that have led to
that apex as being the work of the Holy Spirit. Right? So if now we in a European derived western
culture.
have a new understanding of gender or sexuality or biological sex or any other ethical moral
issue of who God is, whatever, whatever has developed historically in this Western, dare
I say often white, right?
Culture.
Whatever has developed in that culture, this is the work of the Holy Spirit that has brought us to this.
Right. And therefore, it is endorsed and we reshape our theology based on this.
Right. So a new understanding of gender that arises within culture and society is for them,
the work of God has brought that about within society. Yeah. This is where you hear people use
language like the right
of history. Right. And so it doesn't matter if the person questioning that is from the same culture.
Right. But who says, hey, I don't think this is historical to me. They're doing more like what we're
advocating for, which is saying, well, no, we have to sift through this and say, what is from God
and what isn't, right? Or if it's...
someone from another culture who might have another skin color, right?
Might be from another continent.
Right.
Doesn't matter who's questioning it, whoever's questioning it is a
nately backwards.
Is a nately rejecting the work of the Holy Spirit in the world.
Yeah.
This is also where you hear people stuff like people say things like
it's 2023.
Like that's an argument.
It's current year.
Yeah.
But so this you have to understand this is their
understanding, right? And this is why trying to take any kind of approach with them of, well,
but this previous understanding or this thing from the past, no matter what it is, right?
Fundamentally doesn't work, right? Because they have this underlying presupposition.
that their culture now at this point in time is the apex of all human culture
and civilization and that God has brought it there.
Right? This is why when I, when you hear me critiquing liberal theology, it's
often from what sounds like a liberal perspective, right? Like, I'll say to
people who express these ideas, right? They'll be attacking, for example, African
bishops in their own church.
Hmm, for not going along.
What's nice about me using that example is there are at least three different denominations
I could be talking about.
Yes, that's right.
Yes, right.
Right.
Like when they as white bourgeois Americans or Europeans attack African bishops and call
them backwards.
Right.
And all of these things.
you know, for not being on board with their new liberal consensus.
I will call them white supremacists, right?
Because that's what that is.
Colonialism.
Right.
That is colonialism, right?
That it's, yes.
Right.
It's all the things they claim to hate they're actually doing.
Right?
Right.
But that's why I, if people hear me critique it that way, I know some people might get confused.
Right?
Like, but that's why I critique it that way.
that's the only critique that can function on their own.
own presuppositions. Yeah. Right. That's the only critique that's valid from
there based on their own presuppositions. Any critique from tradition is
going to fall flat on its face. Right. Because they've substituted instead of
our understanding for tradition, they have this haggily and understanding of
history. And so trying to talk tradition doesn't work. Right. That's the only
kind of critique.
And that's because ultimately, that line of thinking is in a
rubriose. Right. It's a snake eating a sotail. Yeah. Right.
It's it's it's it's first principles are incoherent. That's why
you can critique their beliefs based on their beliefs. Right.
That's because they don't fit together. Right. But so yeah,
that at the end. This is the deviant view. Right.
how the spirit works and how tradition works that we need to be aware of.
Right? Because I don't think we can have productive dialogue with people who have
imbibed liberal theology and are coming at things from that perspective.
When we come at them from a completely alien perspective, the chairs, none of their
presuppositions. Right? I don't think there's any way for that to be productive.
other than you know
maybe just saying, you have to abandon everything you think you don't change everything, which
may work sometimes, right? And maybe if you show them how self-refuting their own ideas are,
maybe that'll help that happen, right? But there's a fundamental lack of communication
between those who have fallen prey to that kind of liberal theology and the rest of us.
But it would be good for their sakes if we can...
find a bridge to try to bring them back to the truth. But so that said as a final
aggression, right? We come back to a topic that we talked about in our very first
Halloween special, which was what the fifth episode. Yeah, I think so.
And that is the fact that when we talk about replacement in the sense that
Saints in glory, human saints, replace um
Replace fallen angelic beings.
That this is something that takes place in real time.
This takes place in time and space.
And that's because of this synergistic understanding.
So one of the concrete examples we've used repeatedly on the show is Saint Demetrius in
Thessaloniki replacing Aphrodite as the spirit of the
and of the place, and of the polity, of the police, right?
And that is something that happened in real time,
at least in terms of the human experience of it.
Yeah, right?
Yeah.
The phenomenology experience of it, right?
The gospel came there and St. Demetrius was part of the gospel coming there, right?
It started with St. Paul, of course, but right, and part of the process.
and the people of Thessaloniki began
and to realign themselves. Not with Aphrodite. Right? There was a time where it was all
Aphrodite and then it starts to move. Right? And over time, realign themselves with Saint
Dermitrius, who is shepherding them back to God, who had aligned himself with the Holy Spirit,
by aligning with him.
Right?
Like St. Paul said, imitate me as I imitate...
Christ, right? They were brought into alignment with God, right? And so the spirit who was motivating
them, who was shepherding them, right, became Saint Demetrius and ceased being Aphrodite, this played
out in real time, right? And that's what we mean by playing out in real time. This phenomenal
logical sense in the lives of people.
Right?
And so...
This can, as we've been asked, move back and forth.
You look at the sweep of much of history, since Christ's ascension,
and it was moving kind of in one direction with Christendom and everything.
And then lately we see that kind of getting wobbly, maybe.
For any given person, a person can apostatize.
A people group could have ostracized.
A nation could apostatize.
Yep.
Right? Can turn from God.
And begin to be led by something else towards something else.
Right?
Um, but that also means they can always repent and turn back.
All right, well, as we're wrapping up this episode on patron saints,
um,
You know, the thought that really occurs to me in terms of summarizing my own thoughts
about this, well, there's really two, and they're intimately connected, of course.
The first question is, what does salvation really mean?
Because I think sometimes people might, if you bring up patron saints, especially if
they're not from a tradition where this is a thing.
Again, you know, these are mostly our pros.
friends. I mean, I was raised by myself. This was not part of our tradition when I was in that world.
Patron saints might seem like, well, it's a side issue. Like, you know, it's not really,
if you're not against it, maybe you at least you might say, well, it's not really that important
for salvation. Right? So number one, you know, as an Orthodox Christian, I believe that the saints
Let's...
assistance salvation, but that's not really why this is actually important.
It's important because
if you track the whole way, if you track all the stuff that we've said in this whole episode, what you see actually is that
this is the trajectory of the Christian
right, that to be saved
means to be among those whom the scripture says
The Saints.
will judge the world, that the life of the age to come is subjected not to angels, but to humans,
to glorified humans. And so salvation itself is about becoming part of the divine council,
a part of to use sort of raw or language, the council...
the gods. That's what it means to be saved. That's the trajectory of Christianity. That's its purpose
to become as Christ's again. I mean, I've referenced as a gazillion times the podcast, but it bears
repeating. Christ says in Luke chapter 20 that the sons of the resurrection are sons of God and
equal to the angels. That is not a side issue. That's the core. That's right there.
at the middle, right there in the very center of what it means to be Christian.
Suns of the resurrection, sons of God equal to the angels, right?
And so when we look at the saints functioning as patrons, as as spirits who influence and
help to guide in, you know, particular people, peoples, churches, nations, groups, places,
whatever. They are
simply doing the thing that is where the arc of salvation goes. That's the goal. That's the goal
of the Christian life is to function in that way, to share in God's stewardship, his love, his
care for this cosmos. Right? And so the saints are simply people who are doing it.
And the reason that they're doing it, this is the second...
question, you know, what do we therefore do now about this? The reason that they're
doing it is because in this life and in the earthly life that if you're listening to
this, you're part of the earthly life, I'm part of the earthly life, that in this life,
they practiced it. And this life, they did it as much as they could. Now obviously their
capability magnified.
in their passage into the life of the age to come.
And that's why we experienced them in what seems to be super human ways, but is actually
not beyond humanity, but is the destiny of humanity.
Like it's the most human way.
Right?
We are, we're, we function subhumanly.
They're functioning humanly.
But while they were in this life and had to function subhumanly on some level.
they practiced this as much as they could.
They functioned to put this world into order and beauty
and harmony and shepherded themselves
and those around them towards God,
towards that chaste marriage, as we talked about earlier.
And so all the things that we do in order to orient ourselves
and our homes are relational.
our relationships, our jobs, our thoughts, our libraries, our gardens, our kids.
I mean, go on and on.
Whatever you want to put in there.
Everything that we do to do that is
formational, transformational
to become what we see the saints doing now.
That's the goal.
That's what it means to be Christian.
is the purpose of...
Christianity is to be co-enthroned with Christ, to be seated on those thrones next to him, to put the world with him in subordination to him in order.
Just like we see happening in the Old Testament of the Angels, just like we see happening very explicitly in Second Temple Jewish literature,
file-ode jubilee, etc.
just like we see happening in the New Testament, just like we see happening in all of church history.
That's that's what the goal is. And so the the motivator of our Christian life now is to do that.
And the beautiful thing is is we don't do this in an isolated way. We have them to help us and we have
each other as well to help us.
help each other so that we might be seated also in Christ at the right hand of God.
Father Stephen?
So where we sort of ended up tonight was talking about changing spirits, changing the patron
of a place.
or of a people group or of a person or of part of the world.
And the most basic spiritual warfare that I think most of us, or at least most of
people listening right now are called, is expressly this.
Some of us need to change the spirit that's hanging over us.
a person. There's someone or something that we're following that's shepherding us that's guiding us.
We may think it's guiding us toward something like success or wealth or recognition or some feeling
of fulfillment. It's not shepherding us toward destruction.
And we should know that because as we follow it, as we follow its lead and take its guidance,
what we're experiencing is isolation and alienation and resentment and jealousy.
None of which are signs that we're moving in the right direction.
And we need to replace that spirit with another.
with one of the same
who will guide us back toward God, who will show us the way to live a life in
this world as many different lives as we live as many different lives as the
saints have led different places at different times. To make our way back to
God in and through this world and through our day-to-day life. Some of us it's
not maybe.
ourselves. Maybe we're working not that we've arrived but we're working toward
working our way faithfully back toward Christ as faithfully as we can. Maybe not as
faithfully as we ought. But there's a spirit in our family that we can see as
it work and that's the wrong one.
And we can tell it's the wrong one because our family life is marked with
squabbling, bickering, resentments, anger, alienation, dysfunction.
We need to find a way to replace that one with another.
It's good to show our family and shepherd our family and how to live together
as a family in a way that's pleasing.
to God and that will help all of us draw closer to God.
Some of us may be, we're struggling through it and our family is struggling through it,
but maybe our church parish has a spirit that's guiding it that's not the one whose name
is on the door.
Because again there's division, there's resentment, there's a focus on money, there's a focus
on.
prestige. There's a focus on who's getting the attention, who's getting thanked, who's
getting applauded, who has what job. And the work we need to do in our parish is to work
on banishing that spirit, bringing back the one whose name is on the door, and bringing
people together to live our lives together as a community in a way that's
to God, in a way that enables and equips all of us to draw closer to Him. Maybe we've
even got a parish that's not perfect, but we're all struggling together toward Christ.
Maybe it's our neighborhood. Maybe it would be our neighborhood if we knew any of our
neighbors. Maybe it's a pole that's hanging over it. Maybe.
It's just people who have given up, people who are depressed, people who are
despondent, people who don't have hope.
You can tell when you're in that type of neighborhood.
You can tell from the litter.
You can tell from the way people's houses look.
You can tell from the way they don't greet each other or talk to each other
when they see each other.
In all of these cases, making that change,
Banishing the One Spirit.
exercising the One Spirit and bringing in the other to be followed toward God
Isn't something you do with an elaborate ritual?
It isn't something you do by being perfect yourself otherwise we don't be in trouble
It's something you do by doing little things
Little small seemingly inconsequential things over and over and over again
That's what happens when you go and you moe somebody's lawn.
When you cook them a meal, when you see that their kids need new pairs of shoes, see
you buy them shoes, or give them shoes that your kids have outgrown.
When you sit and talk to them and you're kind to them, and you learn your neighbor's
names.
where they're from, what they care about and what they're thinking and feeling.
Just like with Thessaloniki, that example we gave, it doesn't happen overnight.
It took centuries in Thessaloniki.
You're not going to turn things around on a dime.
You're not going to see immediate results.
But slowly but surely as we work.
follow the angels and the saints to follow them back to God and to do that by doing the works of God
and the lives of other people who God has put in our life, has put in our path. The change starts to happen.
Pretty soon we're not the only one working on it. Pretty soon we have help. Pretty soon we have support.
Then things start to change a little more and it goes on and it goes on.
And people and places and groups of people can be transformed this way.
It's happened before.
It's happened in the world through Christianity.
It can happen again in our day.
It's horrible as we all think it is.
But somebody has to make a start.
to start doing those little things.
And if you're listening to this show tonight,
or you're hosting it,
might as well be us.
Those are my thoughts.
Amen.
Well, that's our show for tonight, everyone.
Thank you for listening.
If you didn't get through to us live this time,
we'd still like to hear from you.
You can email us.
The email addresses Lordofspiritsadaintsandfeith.com.
you can
messages at our Facebook page or you can leave us a
voicemail at speakbip.com slash Lord of Spirits and if
you have basic questions about Orthodox Christianity or
you need help finding a parish head over to Orthodoxintro.org.
Enjoy us for a live broadcast on the second four Thursdays of
the month at 7 p.m. Eastern 4 p.m. Pacific. When I die and
they leave me to rest, I'm going to go to the place that's
the best. If you're on Facebook, follow our page and join our
discussion group you can leave reviews and ratings.
everywhere but most importantly share this show with a friend who is going to love it and benefit from it.
I got that reference.
And finally, be sure to go to ancientfaith.com
stroke support and help make sure we and lots of other AFR
podcasters stay on the air.
Prepare yourself.
You know it's a must.
Gotta have a friend in Jesus so you know that when you die,
he's gonna recommend you to the Spirit in the sky.
Thank you, good night.
God bless you.
Christ is born and happy new year to you all.
You've been listening to the Lord.
of spirits, with Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick, and Father
Stephen DeYoung, a listener-supported presentation of ancient faith radio.
And I beheld, and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne.